<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Miles Christianus, or The campe royal set forth in briefe meditations on the words of the Prophet Moses, Deut. 23, 9, 14. here under following, preached in the armie as Dungen-Leager, profitable for all sorts of men to reade; and published for the generall good of all that will read, By Samuel Bachiler, Preacher to the English at Gorinchem.</title>
            <author>Bachiler, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114807</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850030</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15213</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00951)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 871:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Miles Christianus, or The campe royal set forth in briefe meditations on the words of the Prophet Moses, Deut. 23, 9, 14. here under following, preached in the armie as Dungen-Leager, profitable for all sorts of men to reade; and published for the generall good of all that will read, By Samuel Bachiler, Preacher to the English at Gorinchem.</title>
                  <author>Bachiler, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. P[later],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare M. DC. XXV. [1625]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soldiers --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MILES CHRISTIANVS, <hi>OR</hi> THE CAMPE ROYAL Set forth in briefe Meditations on the words of the Prophet Moſes, Deut. 23, 9, 14. here under following, preached in the armie at Dungen-Leager, profitable for all ſorts of men to reade; and publiſhed for the generall good of all that will read, By SAMVEL BACHILER, <hi>Preacher to the Engliſh at Gorinchem.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 23, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When the hoſt goeth forth againſt thine enimies, then keepe thee from everie wicked thing.</p>
               <bibl>verſ. <hi>14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p> For the Lord thy God walketh in the midst of the Campe, to deliver thee, and to giue up thine enimies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee: therefore ſhall thy Campe be holy, that he ſee no uncleane thing in thee, and turne away from thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AMSTERDAM, Printed by R. P. in the yeare M.DC.XXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:15213:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15213:2"/>
            <head>To all my deare and loving Countrimen in ſervice to the States of the Vnited-Provinces: the honourable Officers, and all honeſt Souldiers of the Engliſh nation reſiding in the Netherlands; and specially (as ſervice bindeth me) to thoſe of Gorcom in Holland: <hi>S. B.</hi> wiſheth all happie ſucceſſe, and further acceſſe of true noblenes and worth. And after an end of a weariſome warfare in this life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, eternall welfare in the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Countriemen:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The cauſe we haue to maintaine <hi>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i &amp; armis)</hi> is the ſame in ſubſtance with that which the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites had: they, the defenſe and propagation of Religion in ſpite of the <hi>Canaanites:</hi> we, the <hi>myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call warre</hi> of theſe <hi>Provinces</hi> for the ſame ends, againſt the <hi>Papacie.</hi> And the cauſe remaining, the effect continueth juſtly. What ſimple <hi>Sectarie</hi> might not ſee (if perverſe opinion had not caſt a miſt before his eyes) the urgent cauſe of warrs (the worlds inſurrection againſt the trueth) neceſſarie, and ſo conclude the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in armes borne by us, to withſtand helliſh malice; of no leſſe conſequence, till that be wholly verified <hi>Ieſ. 2, 4. Mich. 4, 3. They ſhall beate their ſwords into plowſhares, and their speares into pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hookes: Nation ſhall not lift up a ſword againſt nation; neyther ſhall they learne warre any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will put enmitie between thee and the woman, and betweene thy ſeed, and her ſeede: it ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe is heele. Gen. 3.15.</hi> is an old quarrell, a grudge inveterate, which will never out. The Church of <hi>God</hi> ever was maligned, ever will be. And <hi>Chriſt</hi> came not to ſend peace, but a ſword; <hi>that is in a word:</hi> to rouſe up the world by accident againſt himſelf, and his <hi>everlaſting Gospell,</hi> which when the world will not receiue, the world will perſequute and proſequute to the extirping of it, if it were poſſible. Yet God defendeth his little flock; but by meanes externall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, though not the moſt potent, ſtrong, and likely in outward
<pb facs="tcp:15213:3"/>ſhew, the which notwithſtanding he is pleaſed to bleſſe for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his.</p>
            <p>And is it not apparant (as though written with the beames of the Sunne) that <hi>God</hi> ſhall put into the hearts of the tenne Hornes (the Kings of the earth) to fulfill his will in the judgment of the Whore by warre againſt her?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17, 16, 17.18, 9.</note> And ſo by outward force overthrow her outward uſurped power, and ſtate politique at length; as by the breath of his mouth, he hath in great meaſure alreadie (and ſo doeth dayly, and will do more and more) and ſhall utterly aboliſh that Spirituall juriſdiction pretended by her <hi>Clyents</hi> to be giuen her.</p>
            <p>So then, your Cauſe (Beloved, wherein with others you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed) is good and ſure: onely looke to it, that miſdemeanour in your warres doe not diſadvantage you. Now, what was ſpoken to the <hi>Warriers</hi> of <hi>God</hi> heretofore; <hi>to doe no evill,</hi> and <hi>to be holy:</hi> may well be ſpoken to us now, and applied as needfully, peradventure more: for, as the world is older it groweth wickeder, and men of all conditions are more diſſolute in this laſt and worſt age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ends of the world are fallen. And, if there were one <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan</hi> then lurking in the Campe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 25, 6.</note> there will be tenne now more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious: and for an impudent paire of <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbie</hi> then, that will come in the ſight of all, while Moſes and the reſt are weeping before the dore of the Tabernacle, many ſkores I feare me now durſt doe as much: and for one <hi>Korah</hi> and his Complices of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiners then, what legions of rebels may we looke for now? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for if ever, it is needfull to preſſe divine law upon us. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But (will ſome ſay) to be ſo ſtrict is a thing ſo difficult. I anſwer:</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Firſt therefore it requireth your greater heedfulnes, and to be ſo much the more circumſpect.</p>
            <p>Secondly, were it not hard to doe, it were leſſe praiſe-worthie to doe, but being difficult, it will argue the more ſpirit in thee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it ſufficeth that it is poſſible in ſome meaſure to doe Euangelically, if we be carefull: ſo that the difficultie is not ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute to excuſe us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſome practiſe &amp; proofe of holy reſolution will make it more tollerable, onely get a deſire from God, to approue thy ſelf unto him. But, he that refreineth himſelf from evill maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a prey. True, a prey to evill men, to whoſe diſgrace and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie he cannot but expoſe and proſtrate himſelfe (for by and by,
<pb facs="tcp:15213:3"/>he is a <hi>Puritan</hi> or <hi>Preciſian,</hi> (
<note n="*" place="margin">Bottondiſe. of true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse.</note> honourable nicknames of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and grace) that will not giue freedome and libertie to himſelfe, though it be to damne his owne ſoule) but while they giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the raines to all evill, they make themſelues a prey to the Divell.</p>
            <p>Having by occaſion thought upon the ſubject of my enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to explaine and apply thoſe words of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how behoofefull it might be for theſe times, I haue thought to giue it further vent, eſpecially upon the judgment and approbation of ſome godly-learned, deeming it might be uſefull; hoping, that as the leaſt haire hath it ſhadow, ſo the leaſt endeavour of good might doe ſome good.</p>
            <p>Thus much would I craue of you, to whom I appropriate this, what ever it is. Firſt to accept of an honeſt purpoſe and intent in him who wiſheth he could be more ſerviceable to you, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>Gods</hi> Church. And ſure I am, the good and honeſt will not reject it, becauſe they will ſee, and I truſt ſay, he meant well, and had a minde to further us in pietie: As for the Prophane, while he ſcoffeth me, I will pittie and pray for him. Secondly, Vouchſafe to put it up in your pockets, and at your Vacancie read this litle ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall. This my minde doeth giue me, you will ſay doeth pleaſe you: He is not prolixe by extravagant digreſſions from the purpoſe of the words, or obſervations therein taken up; if any thing els doth ſavour with you, I hope it will the more profit you. The <hi>Ship</hi> that putteth out to ſea hath his helme and Pilot to govern her.
<note place="margin">Iames 3.</note> The <hi>horſe</hi> that is taken up for a journey, his bridle to rule him (for their mouths muſt be kept in with bit and bridle. <hi>Pſal. 32, 9.</hi>) And when we goe out to war againſt our enimies, <hi>Gods</hi> law muſt order us, turn us about, and bridle our wayes. If this little unworthy thing proue better then I can preſage it wil, I ſhal be the more willing to publiſh another
<note place="margin">" Eſsaies on Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, wherein the proprietie of the Hebrew &amp; what the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, &amp; Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins haue uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is ſet down: paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel places of the Scripture conferred; and matter of obſervation throughout that booke of the Lords wars; Whereof I may ſay: Venit ſilius uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad matricem: ſed non est virtus ad pariendum.</note> ſubject, at this time by me, for fitter oportunitie when it ſerveth. In the meane time I commend this to your practiſe, and you all to <hi>Gods</hi> grace, and remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in Chirſt: <hi>Samuel Bachiler.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="afterword_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15213:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader whoſoever. An admonitorie Poſtſcript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It may be, when thou ſeest the title in the <hi>frontiſpiece,</hi> and readeſt the text, thou wilt think, that as the profeſsion whereunto thou art a ſtranger, (as ſuppoſe no Souldier) ſo the matter of this book concerns thee not, who perhaps art a <hi>Burger,</hi> or homedweller. But let not this hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der further inſpection; and let me aſsure thee, that what is here ſpoken to them abroad, doth deeply concerne thee at home, though thou ſhouldſt never be called, or once constreined to follow that courſe of life. For this being a Scripture-ſubject is profitable for all. And howſoever we haue too much cauſe to lament the vices, the outrages, the enormities of the Camp; yet know thou, and confeſſe, that all ſin is not there alone. And take theſe words of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be ſpoken to thee alſo, whoſe calling is dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique and at home, in towne or countrey: <hi>When the hoſt goeth forth to warre, then keepe thee</hi> (euen <hi>thee,</hi> who stayest at home for thy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie employments) <hi>from everie wicked thing.</hi> Keepe thou thy ſelfe I ſay, from the tap-houſe, the whorehouſe, the play-houſe; and the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evils of thoſe accurſed places. Keepe thee from idlenes, and be diligent in thy calling, and in the holy exerciſes of prayer, hearing, and meditating <hi>Gods</hi> word, &amp;c. And let us feare, leaſt not onely their ſinnes abroad, but our ſinnes at home alſo, doe help mightily to pull the wrath of <hi>God</hi> upon them, who for our ſakes are employed abroad, and endure the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching heate, and the pinching cold, while we ſit ſtill under our own vines. Yea this concerneth you <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> publique or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, to looke to good order in your townes and families, and that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane libertie be not giuen to breake the <hi>Sabbaoths,</hi> to frequent and weare the threſholds of ryotous places, for heatheniſh <hi>May-games,</hi> and <hi>Whitſon-ales</hi> (as they call their mad ſports.) And ſuffer not youth to diſ-order themſelues as they doe, to the ſhame and ſcandall of thoſe places where they are. Oh, what neede haue we in theſe troublous times, when the hoſt is gone forth to warre upon our enimies, to be more carefull of our
<pb facs="tcp:15213:4"/>ſelues and ours at home, if (as I hope we doe) we wiſh proſperitie to thoſe who are gone out. We haue more neede to giue our ſelues to watch, and pray, and faſt and mourne for their ſinnes and our owne, and <hi>to cover the Altar of the Lord with teares,</hi> that ſo he may haue mercie upon us.</p>
            <p>You that are at home, and worthily complaine of the ſinnes of the hoſt, looke into your townes, and citties, and houſes, and be aſhamed of the ſtewes and brothel-houſes among you, ſhamefully connived at under the noſe of Authoritie, by thoſe whom <hi>God</hi> will charge, for having ſo little heart, and zeale, and courage, and conſcience to ſuppreſse them. Looke and behold the breaches of the <hi>Sabaoth</hi> by carriage and re-carriage, looke into the beastly exceſſe of drunkennes, chambering and wantonnes among you. Is your hoſt gone forth to warre, &amp; are you (o Citizens) free at home, to commit all uncleanneſſe, and that with greedines? Know, that for theſe things unreformed, and perſiſted in without repentance, <hi>God</hi> will ſearch you out with lights, and viſit thoſe that ſit frozen upon their dregs. Know, you are to guard againſt evill at home in your ſtreets and houſes, as they that are abroad, to withhold from evill in their Campes. For is it not all one, whether their ſinnes abroad, or yours at home, doe undoe and marre all lawfull deſignes? <hi>2 Sam. 11, 11.</hi> The arke &amp; Iſrael and Iudah abide in tents, and the ſervants of my Lord Ioab encamp in the open fields, ſhall I then goe into mine houſe, and eate and drinke, and lye with my wife? &amp;c. As their Camps therefore ſhould be holy Camps; ſo ſhould your houſes alſo be holy, that holynes dwelling in your ſtreets and houſes, <hi>God</hi> who walketh in the mids of their Camps, may ſee no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſse in you, and may walke in your ſtreets and houſes, and take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to dwell among you, and his ſoule may not abhorre you. Refuſe not then to take up this, whoſoever thou art, and make that uſe thereof which thou mayſt doe. And <hi>God</hi> bleſſe the reading of it to thee. To <hi>God</hi> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thee, and the word of his grace. and bid thee farewell, and am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, if thou wilt make uſe of me. <hi>S. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:15213:5"/>
            <head>In Rev. Doctiſſimique viri <hi>D. SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ELIS BACHILERI,</hi> Militem Chriſtianum.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beata Caſtra, quae ſuprema Numinis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Autoritate diriguntur unicè!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſtra ô tremenda Copiis vel maximis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hostis ferocis, praepotentis, impij!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illis Bilhami nullius ſacri doli</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leviſſimum molirier malum queunt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>En ergò Christi qui gregem defenditis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Recta hîc docetur ſemita ad victoriam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vtare Miles hoc libello; &amp; tu, Dei</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sincere cultor, quiſquis es; benè rem geres.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohannes Spiljardus, <hi>Eccleſiaſtes Gorinchemenſis.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>Proſopopaeia <hi>PIETATIS,</hi> optantis intereſſe &amp; praeeſſe Caſtris Chriſtianorum, juxta Dei Oracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum egregiè illuſtratum à D. S. B</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>IPſa ego, quâ ſolâ poſſit benedicier Armis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E Caſtris PIET AS cogor abireprocul.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O utinam Chriſti qui nomine Caſtra ſequuntur</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me Comitem vellent atque Ducem eſſe ſibi!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic nunquam miſerè caderent hoſtilibus armis;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hostibus ast ipſis damna parata forent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oraculum Summi Ducis hoc testatur abundè</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic SAMVEL cuius Praeco fidelis adeſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Idem.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:15213:5"/>
            <head>Of M. Samuel Bachiler his Campe-Royall or Campe-Chriſtian.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE <hi>Campe</hi>'s a <hi>Schole,</hi> where th'underſtanding part</l>
               <l>Improuement makes, in everie <hi>Liberall art.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi>practiſe</hi> perfects, what in bookes we learne;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Dullards</hi> from the <hi>pregnant</hi> doth diſcerne.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Campe</hi> 's a <hi>Court,</hi> where all <hi>Heroick ſeedes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Courage, freedome, Nobleſſe, vertue</hi> breedes,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>natiue comelynes</hi> is <hi>man-like braue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>inward worth</hi> may <hi>unbought</hi> honour haue.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Campe</hi>'s a <hi>Theater,</hi> where men <hi>truly doe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What others wonder at to ſee in <hi>ſhew.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where ſome do <hi>act</hi> braue deedes, that others may</l>
               <l>Liue afterwards, by acting them in <hi>play.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Camp</hi>'s a <hi>Cittie, Diſcipline</hi> the lawe,</l>
               <l>Which doth incourage <hi>Grace,</hi> keepes <hi>vice in awe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi>order</hi> rules within, and round about</l>
               <l>The <hi>armed-living walls</hi> keepes danger out.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Campe</hi>'s a <hi>world,</hi> where men at once may ſee</l>
               <l>With litle travell, what varieties be</l>
               <l>In ſeverall Countries, and with eaſie toyle</l>
               <l>Fetch home the <hi>goulden glories</hi> of each ſoyle.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Campe</hi>'s a <hi>Church,</hi> where God is truely ſerved,</l>
               <l>And where the faythfull are in <hi>death</hi> preſerved</l>
               <l>From <hi>laſting danger;</hi> for his numerous hoſt</l>
               <l>Of <hi>warlike Angels</hi> pitch where danger's moſt.</l>
               <l>Then idle <hi>Truant,</hi> from this <hi>Schole</hi> depart.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Sloven,</hi> get thee from this <hi>Court</hi> to Cart.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Coward</hi> goe make faces at a <hi>play,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There <hi>ſtand</hi> and fight, that here didſt <hi>runne</hi> away.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Drudge</hi> to thy <hi>yoake,</hi> thou art no <hi>free-man</hi> here.</l>
               <l>And wandring <hi>Puffe,</hi> ſeeke <hi>ſuites</hi> and <hi>belly-cheere.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Divell</hi> get thee from the <hi>Church,</hi> from the <hi>elect;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>"One Achan may an hoſt of Saints infect.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vaine-glorious <hi>Pride,</hi> that over-valueſtall</l>
               <l>Thy owne hand doth, making great things of ſmall.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15213:6"/>
               <l>Effeminate <hi>floath,</hi> that dar'ſt not march, watch, fight;</l>
               <l>Whom winde, raine, cold, heate, hunger doth affright.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Envie</hi> that doſt detract from others worth,</l>
               <l>And ſmothereſt due deſert from ſhining forth.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luſt</hi> that the bodie weakens, and the minde</l>
               <l>Makes feminine, as if it altered kinde.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Drinke</hi> that doſt waſh witte, wealth, and worth away,</l>
               <l>And like a <hi>whoore</hi> thy lovers doſt <hi>betray.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Foole-frantike Furie</hi> that doeſt, Aiax-like,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>friend</hi> with <hi>fiſt,</hi> thy <hi>God</hi> with <hi>curſes</hi> ſtrike.</l>
               <l>Curſt <hi>Avarice</hi> that grind'ſt the poore to duſt,</l>
               <l>And let'ſt the ſouldiar <hi>ſtarue</hi> to <hi>feede</hi> thy luſt;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Avant to Hell,</hi> and leaue the honored traine,</l>
               <l>Who loue <hi>religion,</hi> and count <hi>grace a gaine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For here thou read'ſt all <hi>cloudie vices</hi> dampe,</l>
               <l>The <hi>glorious splendor</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Campe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which ſhould reſemble heauen, where <hi>Michael</hi> fought</l>
               <l>With the <hi>old Dragon,</hi> and his rebell rout,</l>
               <l>And caſt them headlong downe: ſo chace away</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Serpentine ſinne,</hi> which doth thy ſoule betray</l>
               <l>To <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi> then looke to <hi>outward foes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For <hi>theſe</hi> o're-come, becauſe we yeelde to <hi>thoſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This BACHILER moſt clerely hath expreſt.</l>
               <l>And who art thou, that wilt be to the reſt</l>
               <l>A <hi>Divell</hi> to tempt, as he a <hi>Saint</hi> hath bin</l>
               <l>To teach, to woe, to weane thy ſoule from ſinne?</l>
               <l>Him imitate, abhor thine owne baſe minde,</l>
               <l>Which wert of <hi>God-like,</hi> art of <hi>Divel-like</hi> kinde.</l>
               <l>And if thou think'ſt, I praiſe the <hi>Campe</hi> too much;</l>
               <l>Know but for thee, it is, or would be ſuch.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. SCOT <hi>Miniſter to the Engliſh in Virecht.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15213:6"/>
            <head>MILES CHRISTIANVS, <hi>OR</hi> THE CAMPE ROYAL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut. 23, 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When the hoſt goeth forth againſt thine enimies, then keepe thee from everie wicked thing.</p>
                  <bibl>verſ. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>For the Lord thy God walketh in the midst of the Campe. &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lawes and ordinances for <hi>Iſrael</hi> were various, according to their ſeverall States and occaſions: And for as much as they had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie enimies to interrupt and trouble their peace, by a kinde of neceſſitie they muſt wage warre; therefore in ſundrie places we finde many whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes &amp; ordinances for that alſo. Here in particular we meete with orders from <hi>God,</hi> by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> to them. The <hi>Order</hi> in theſe two verſes giuen, is <hi>negatiue</hi> in the 9 ver. <hi>affirmatiue</hi> in the 14 verſe, which (by reaſon of a fit coherence betweene them) I haue joyned together.</p>
            <p>In the words of the 9 verſe two things are generally to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15213:7"/>be noted: 1, The <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of a precept, to <hi>forbeare all evill.</hi> 2, The <hi>circumſtance</hi> of the time, when that precept is moſt to be regarded; viz. <hi>when the hoſt goeth forth,</hi> which is the time of warre.</p>
            <p>The hoſt] <hi>mahhaneh,</hi> ſo called from encamping or quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Yet</hi> tetze <hi>going before</hi> mahhaneh <hi>may be of forme maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, according alſo as the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, Italian, French, our former Engliſh and other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions read; When thou go est forth &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> otherwiſe called <hi>tſaba,</hi> importing order for battail. When the hoſt goeth forth] <hi>Mahhaneh</hi> though of the common gender is here made feminine by the forme of the verbe: though ſuch ſhould not their mindes be, that go out like an armie, but maſculine and manlike. Againſt thine enimie] or, upon thine enimie, viz. to battell, as ch. 20, 1.21, 10. to warre. An uſuall <hi>Ellipſis</hi> of the verbe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, eaſie to be underſtood and ſupplied.</p>
            <p>The <hi>antecedent</hi> part of the words occaſion this obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the firſt place, (in that <hi>Moſes</hi> ordereth their going out to warre, and ſpeakes of the <hi>ſubiect</hi> of their warre, an <hi>enimie,</hi> ſaying; <hi>When the hoſt goeth forth againſt thine enimie.) Obſerve.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> There muſt be no warres, but againſt an enimie, and againſt a true enimie there may be warres.</hi> Which point hath two branches.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 11. <hi>Such were the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites upon whom they went out.</hi>
               </note> 1, The <hi>ſubject againſt whom we warre muſt be our enimie.</hi> He ſpeaks not of going out ſimply, as if it were no matter againſt whom they went out, but of going out upon an <hi>enimie.</hi> An <hi>enimie</hi> ſeeking their hurte, <hi>Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies invading,</hi> unquiet, turbulent <hi>enimies,</hi> &amp; ſuch as would oppreſſe them,
<note place="margin">Iuſtice is the ſame to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that a foundation is to an houſe.</note> 
               <hi>Num.</hi> 10, 9. The reaſon is; 1, we muſt looke as neare as may be, that our warre be a juſt war. <hi>That which is altogether just ſhalt thou follow, Deut.</hi> 16, 20. That warre is no juſt warre, where it is not againſt an <hi>enimie.</hi> 2. That it may appeare, we are not a people that delight in war, who haue a curſe denounced againſt them <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68, 30. <hi>Scatter the people that delight in warre;</hi> who out of a delight to proue troubleſome to neighbour-bordering nations, ever &amp; anon put occaſions of warre on foote. 3, It is againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15213:7"/>of warre, to be moved againſt any but an <hi>enimie.</hi> Such <hi>hostilitie</hi> is a plaine <hi>robberie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſect. This therefore warreth againſt the practiſe of thoſe, 1, who will goe out to warre upon any humour whatſoever, and not alwaies againſt an <hi>enimie,</hi> but againſt ſuch as wrong them not, to make a vaine oſtentation of their might, and what they are able to doe, to enlarge their borders, and make their names grow great in the world: Then which, what more wicked, out of meere ambition to make combuſtions among men? <hi>Deviſe not evill,</hi> ſayth the wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3, 29. <hi>against thy neighbour, ſeeing he dwelleth ſecurely by thee.</hi> And the Prophet threatneth a <hi>woe Ieſ,</hi> 33, 1. againſt ſuch as are ſo unreaſonablie forward to ſpoile, when they were not ſpoyled. <hi>Woe to thee that ſpoyleſt and wast not ſpoyled,</hi> that <hi>dealeſt treacherouſly and they dealt not treacherouſly with thee, when thou ceaſeſt to ſpoile thou ſhalt be ſpoiled, and when thou ſhalt make an ende to deale treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, they ſhall deale treacherouſly with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This is againſt them alſo, who are readie for any em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in wars, whether againſt freind or foe, they care not, ſo they may finde paye, bootie, and preye, regarding onely their owne private ends, and particular gaines. Such whether they be <hi>enimies</hi> or no, againſt whom they goe in ſervice of war, ſhall giue an account to <hi>God</hi> for their going out: and may looke, never to goe in again, in peace.</p>
            <p>The ſecond branch of the obſervation is, <hi>that againſt an enimie there may be wars,</hi> and the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth not diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it. <hi>Gods</hi> word doth not take away wars upon juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, onely it ordereth them. It takes away the abuſe of wars, but not the uſe, where there is juſt cauſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 17, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>When</hi> (ſayth <hi>Moſes) the hoſt goeth forth to warre, &amp;c.</hi> It is lawfull &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable then to goe forth to war in ſome caſes, but when needs we muſt: this is the rule of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15213:8"/>looke well unto our ſelues, as afterward we ſhall ſee. See <hi>Deutr.</hi> 20, at large, and 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8, 44. <hi>If my people goe out to war against their enimie, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leaſt any object and ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> this was the old time, when things were otherwiſe, now we haue a new Law, and the caſe is not alike.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Anſ. Let us ſee from that new law (which yet in ſubſtance is not another law) under the N. T. moſt cleare and evident places. <hi>Luke</hi> 3, 12, 13, 14. where manie comming to know their duetie, among the reſt, the <hi>Sould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jers</hi> they reſorte to <hi>Iohn,</hi> to learne what they ſhould doe, who inſtructeth them to a harmeles life, not to be rude, but diſapproues not of their profeſſion, onely he laboureth to bring them to a lawfull uſe of it. Moreover, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9, 7. <hi>Who goeth a warfare any time at his owne charges?</hi> &amp; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 4. <hi>No man that goeth a warfare, entangleth himſelf in the affaires of this life.</hi> In both which places, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth honourable mention of wars, duely undertaken. The reaſon is: juſt warres are grounded upon the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which requires defence of our ſelues, and reſcuing of ours. So <hi>Abraham</hi> goes out to redeeme his kinſman <hi>Lot,</hi> and to recover his goods,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Which was approved verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>though he took up armes not by any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement from God, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 14, 14. When <hi>Abraham</hi> heard, that his brother was taken captiue, he armed his <hi>trained</hi> ſervants, &amp;c. grounded alſo upon the law of <hi>God,</hi> which requires defence of religion. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fruite hereof in a juſt quarrell (the ſlaughter of <hi>Gods</hi> enimies) is called the <hi>worke of the Lord. Ier.</hi> 48, 10. <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he, that doth the worke of the Lord negligently, and that withholdeth his ſword from blood.</hi> Now, it cannot be <hi>Gods</hi> worke, but in a calling, which <hi>God</hi> alloweth. It is alſo a worke of fayth. For the Lords worthies <hi>Heb.</hi> 11, 32, 33. are ſaid by fayth to haue ſubdued kingdomes. In which place, as the courſe of the Apoſtles diſſertation ſheweth, under fayth is comprehended a perſwaſion, whereby is beleeved,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15213:8"/>that what is done is well-pleaſing unto God.</p>
            <p>This then may encourage, ſettle, and aſſure you in your way. <hi>Onely be ſtrong, and verie couragious. Ioſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Let your hands be strengthned, and be ye valiant.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. <hi>Be of good courage, and let us play the men for our people, and for the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our God.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10, 12 But of this by the way. The conſequent part of the words, and that which is of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt conſequence, is that which he warnes them of, when they draw forth. In theſe words, <hi>then keepe thee from everie wicked thing. Then]</hi> at that time eſpecially <hi>keepe thee]</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, take heede: The <hi>Hebr.</hi> may anſwer here to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a militarie word uſed for guarding, ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 4, 7. the peace of God ſhall keepe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall guard your hearts 1 <hi>Petr.</hi> 1, 5. <hi>kept by the power of God</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) guarded. So when <hi>Moſes</hi> bids them keepe themſelues, it is ſuch a keeping, as is a moſt ſpeciall guarding of themſelues: it may anſwer alſo to that other word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſometime of the ſame ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in our <hi>Saviours</hi> Sermons. <hi>From everie wicked thing] [dhabbar]</hi> is both a <hi>word</hi> and a <hi>worke</hi> or buſines. And then, here is forbidden, wickednes in word or in deed, whether <hi>morall</hi> or <hi>ceremoniall,</hi> as afterward. There be two ſorts of evill things, as evill aire, yll dyet, cold, heat, in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, &amp; this naturall diſcretion ſheweth a man to keepe himſelfe from, and no neede was there to ſpeake hereof, for as everie thing doth naturally ſeeke it good, ſo doth it avoide the contrarie. 2, There is the evill of ſinne, &amp; that is it, which is here forbidden: and firſt he bids them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of evill, and ſecondly to beware of all evill. The <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatian</hi> is; <hi>when we are going to confront our enimies,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> we must then eſpecially take heede of ſinne. Evill</hi> is to be taken heede of alwaies; we haue no libertie at one time to be more free for ſinn, then at other times ſimplie. <hi>Gods</hi> word doth never conniue at our extravagancies and excurſions
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15213:9"/>to evill. <hi>Sinne</hi> is alwaies perillous, &amp; full of danger to our ſoules and bodies; <hi>Sinne</hi> alway ſtandeth in our light, and is a croſſe barre in our wayes; there never came good of <hi>ſinn</hi> at any time. But there are ſome times of more ſpeciall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdiction, and of worſe conſequence if we <hi>ſinn,</hi> and when there ought to be ſtricteſt watch againſt <hi>evill.</hi> At ſome times it may be more perillous, doe more ſcath and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> For it might be here objected; why then at other times we need not care, or be ſo cautious againſt <hi>evill.</hi> Not ſo,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> but the meaning is, though at all times we are to looke to our ſelues, yet at this time, when we goe to warre, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially. <hi>And take heede to your ſelues</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>leaſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with ſurfeting, and druncken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and cares of this life, and ſo that day come upon you una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares.</hi> Take heede (ſayth he) <hi>least at any time:</hi> He giveth no time of ſinning. <hi>Watch ye therefore and pray alwaies,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour</hi> addeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> when he came home from the warres, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his vowe, kept himſelfe from medling with the goods of that <hi>king,</hi> which to haue received, had beene a wicked thing. See <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 6, 18. <hi>And you in any wiſe keepe your ſelues from the accurſed thing</hi> (all ſinne is an accurſed thing) <hi>leaſt ye make your ſelues accurſed, when ye take of the accurſed thing, and make the campe of Iſrael a curſe and trouble it.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11, 11. <hi>Vriah</hi> ſayd unto <hi>David, The arke and Iſrael and Iudah abide in tents, and my Lord Ioab, and the ſervants of my Lord are encamped in the open field, ſhall I then goe into mine houſe, to eate, and to drinke, and to lye with my wife; as thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest, and as thy ſoule liveth, I will not doe this thing.</hi> Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever failed therein, he would not, though things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues not unlawfull, onely at that time unſeaſonable. The reaſons are manie and weightie, why we ſhould then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare ſinne aboue all.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15213:9"/>
            <p>The firſt is, leaſt evill weaken us before our <hi>Enimies,</hi> &amp; ſo we become a fit prey unto them, in the juſt judgment of <hi>God. Sinne</hi> takes away thoſe ſpirits, that life, that heart from men, which ought to be in them at ſuch times. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4, 11. <hi>Wine and strong drinke, and whoredome take away the heart.</hi> In the 20 of <hi>Deut.</hi> they are bid not to feare, but ſin &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes doth juſtly diſanimate. Nothing in the world doth ſo emaſculate a man (&amp; as it were unman him) as <hi>ſin</hi> doth. <hi>Sin</hi> will cut our ſinewes, and diſioint us, wholly enfeeble, and diſarme us in the ſight of our enemies. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32, 25. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 28, 19. the people were made <hi>naked</hi> before their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>[pharang]</hi> is to ſtrip or draw off, uncover. What, did <hi>Aaron</hi> or <hi>Iudah</hi> take their armour from them? in no wiſe, but had occaſioned <hi>God</hi> (for the ſinne they cauſed them to commit) to take his armour of defenſe from them. Stript them they had in a manner, of <hi>Gods</hi> wonderfull and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie protection, and ſo they were as a people ſtark naked. Their defenſe &amp; protection was gone from them, as is ſaid <hi>Num.</hi> 14, 9. <hi>Feare them not, they are bread for us: their defenſe is departed from them.</hi> the meaning is, <hi>God</hi> had left them for their wickednes, and ſo they became naked, and as weak as water. Deprived they were of the power and providence of Almightie <hi>God,</hi> for that time. Though we haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe in the world, if we haue <hi>Gods</hi> protection, &amp; his arme over us, we want no furniture and covering: on the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, if we haue all outward fenſe, wanting <hi>Gods</hi> protection, we are but bare and open to our enimies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> we cannot do evill then, without great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, inaſmuch as we haue leaſt time to repent us of any evill done. Our dayes are never of the longeſt. <hi>What is your life?</hi> ſayth <hi>Iames,</hi> it is <hi>euen a vapour, which appeareth for a litle time, and then it vaniſheth.</hi> If our liues be alwaies ſo momentanie, much more when we goe with the hoſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15213:10"/>againſt our enimies. Souldiers are ſpecially <hi>mortis ſtipendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arij.</hi> We neede not proue unto you the evidence of this, which experience in the wars doth ever ſhew: yet for our remembrance, looke upon theſe places of Scripture, where you ſhall ſee the hazards of the wars. <hi>Deut.</hi> 20, 5, 6, 7. order is giuen for ſuch and ſuch to returne, &amp; the reaſon is, from verie great likelihood, <hi>leaſt they dye in battell. Iudg.</hi> 9, 17. <hi>My father</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>fought for you, and adventured his life far.</hi> So that, the life of a man in the wars is in the greateſt perill, &amp; venture that may be: 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11, 25. <hi>The ſword devoureth one as well as another.</hi> Chap. 15, 21. <hi>Surely, in what place my Lord the King ſhall be, whether in death or life, there will thy ſervant be.</hi> 18, 3. <hi>Thou ſhalt not goe forth</hi> (ſaid the people to the king) <hi>for if we flee away, they will not care for us, neither if half of us die, will they care for us, &amp;c.</hi> by all which we may ſee the continuall hazards we are in: at that time we carrie our liues in our hands, and there is but a ſtep betweene us and death. What time will there be, or place for repentance, in caſe we doe, eſpecially if we will, ſinne. Then to ſinne muſt needs be a ſinning, <hi>with a high hand,</hi> and preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, when we know, that for that, and other reaſons, we ought then to ſinne leaſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how heynouſly was <hi>God</hi> offended with the whole hoſt of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Ioſua</hi> for the ſinne of <hi>Achan, Ioſ.</hi> 6. and <hi>Num.</hi> 25, with all the people, yea with the <hi>Heads,</hi> v. 45. <hi>Take all the heads of the people, &amp; hang them up before the Lord against the Sunne, &amp;c.</hi> Num. 16. <hi>And they fell upon their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; ſaid, O God, the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh, ſhall one man ſinne, and wilt thou be wroth with all the Congregation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe it is the greateſt honour, when the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions are greateſt, to be abſtemious from ſinne. At other times perhaps, we haue not that freedome of our ſelues, we cannot alwaies do the evill we would, we are pent and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15213:10"/>walled in perhaps, then if we do no evill, it is no marvail, but when the dore is open, as it were, and we haue more oportunitie to ſinne abroad, then not to ſinne, is a greater glorie. As it is a greater grace to abſtaine from druncken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſurfeting at feaſts &amp; meetings, when the occaſions will be more, becauſe of more freedome and plentie of the creatures, &amp; becauſe of the vile provocations through pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane healths, which one or other commonly puts afoote. And change of <hi>place</hi> brings change of <hi>objects. Achan</hi> had not had the occaſion but there where he was, to haue play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the thief. And for <hi>Achan</hi> to abſteine at other times, was no praiſe to <hi>Achan,</hi> but then to haue forborn, had been his glorie. <hi>If thou faint in the day of adverſitie</hi> (or, if thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in the day of ſtreights) <hi>thy ſtrength is ſmall,</hi> (or, nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is thy vertue) <hi>Prov.</hi> 24, 10. If thou ſheweſt not thy ſelf a man, when occaſions come upon thee, thy reſolution and courage is but weake.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, he that hath power over himſelf abroad, will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly keep him ſelf at home. Let a man liue <hi>ſoberly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.</note> godly, and righteouſly</hi> abroad, and ſuch a one ſhall be ſafer from evill doing at home.</p>
            <p>Sixtly and laſtly, we ſhould ſo minde our calling <hi>(hoc a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere)</hi> and be ſo employed and exerciſed, ſo intent and taken up therein, as to finde no leaſure to ſinne.</p>
            <p>This ſerues for complaint, for (alas!) when are we more ſinfull, we runne into forbidden evill, becauſe it is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and then eſpecially, when it is moſt forbidden. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant is our nature, ſuch peccant humours are we repleat of, unleſſe purged with a great deale of grace. It is this doth aggravate our ſinn, that we then ſin moſt, when &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ought to ſin leaſt. We are ſinfull enough at home, but when we are gone forth with the hoſt, to fight againſt the common adverſarie, then, then we are exceſſiue, &amp; fall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15213:11"/>together by the eares, &amp; fight unmanly one with another, then we ring of prophanenes, then towne and countrie, &amp; all places where we come, are filled with the noiſe and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of our evils, our drinking, and drabbing, &amp; ſtabbing, and pillaging without reſpect of perſons. I wiſh we might not ſpeake ſo often of theſe things. Tis no pleaſure to us, to grate your eares with the unpleaſant and harſh ſound hereof. Yet, as he that will haue his ſores cured, muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to be touched, yea ſometime launced: ſo, if you will haue theſe evils healed, you muſt heare of them, and ſometime with bitter reproofe to them.</p>
            <p>Is this to keep us from evill, to run into the wilfull and headie practiſe thereof, <hi>as the horſe ruſheth into the battell?</hi> And is it not uſually ſeene,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> that manie come ſober and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill at leaſt, to the warrs: but when once the hoſt is gone forth, and they with it, they do as much forget goodnes, as though they had never knowne, or beene where it grew. And yet ſome of them, haue had good education, graue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, ſweet plantations, and haue ſproute up with the bloſſomes of hope: ſome of them haue had religious care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parents, who haue ſown them with the feeds of mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie toward men, true pietie toward <hi>God,</hi> who yet, when they betake themſelues to the warres, looſe all civilitie, all frugalitie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let this admoniſh you to looke better to your ſelues, for keeping your ſelues from ſinne, as at all times, ſo in the Campe, eſpecially. Haue ſpeciall care, when the hoſt goeth forth to battell againſt your enimie, to doe no wicked thing. <hi>Take ye therefore</hi> (ſayth <hi>Moſes) Deut.</hi> 4, 15. <hi>good heed unto your ſelues, leaſt you corrupt your ſelues.</hi> So, be more then ordinarily carefull, that no unſeemely thing be done by you, or any of you, at that time aboue all other. Lay all thoſe foreſaid reaſons before you, and conſider well what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15213:11"/>arguments diſſwaſiue they may be unto you, from ſinne and wickednes, when we are come out with the hoſt to war. And firſt, remember how it may weaken your hands, enfeeble your hearts, ſo that when you ſhal think your ſelues, in a manner, <hi>bewitched,</hi> it is nothing but <hi>ſinne</hi> hath done it. <hi>Ieſ. 33, 14. The ſinners in Sion are afraid, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes hath ſurprized the hypocrites.</hi> And that, which is your weakenes, ſhall proue your <hi>enimies</hi> ſtrength, not the ſins which they do, who know no better, but the ſins which you do. The danger of ſin is not ſmall, the prophet <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> would dehort them from it, as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thing moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious. Sin is deadly &amp; hurtfull, in as much as it takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our ſtrength from us, &amp; giveth ſtrength to the <hi>eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> againſt us. You know, how eaſily <hi>Iſrael</hi> was vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the ſin of <hi>Achan. Balaam</hi> and <hi>Balak</hi> would haue wiſhed no more, then that <hi>Iſrael</hi> might haue been more inſnared with ſin, whereby they ſhould ſoone haue felt alteration. <hi>Sin</hi> cutteth off our locks, as <hi>Dalilah</hi> did <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſons. Sin</hi> is as <hi>poyſon,</hi> which when a man hath taken in, his haire, his nailes fall off, &amp; teeth looſen in his head: Such a poyſon is ſin to the bodie of an <hi>Armie,</hi> to the heart of man, it maketh all ſtrength to fall from him, &amp; whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſolveth him in a manner. It is like the fiſh <hi>Torpedo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noue.</note> which with her deadly, &amp; Narcotick force, benummeth the hand of him, who commeth near to catch her. In a word, it is like the <hi>Remora,</hi> which beyond admiration ſtayes our courſe, as <hi>Caius</hi> the <hi>Emperours</hi> ſhip,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. lib.</hi> 32, <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> when the whole fleete went forward; which while they won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, and ſearch was made, they found that little crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cleaving to the Rudder. Is that it (quoth he) with indignation, that withholds me? It is ſtoried of the <hi>Iewes</hi> that while they ſinned not, they proſpered.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudith.</hi> 5.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Becauſe God</hi> (ſaith that <hi>Ammonitiſh</hi> captain) <hi>who hateth iniquitie was with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15213:12"/>them.</hi> But, when they departed from the way he ſet them in, <hi>they were deſtroyed, led captiue, had their temple caſt downe. And now one thing</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>ſhall be their ruine, if there be any fault by ſinne against God in this people, euen this ſhall be their ruine, let us go up, for we ſhall foile them: but if there be no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie among them</hi> (that is, if they haue kept themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> everie wicked thing) <hi>let my Lord</hi> (ſayth he to the Generall) <hi>paſse by, for we can prevaile nothing. They will haue the honour, and we ſhall goe by the ſhame.</hi> For which ſpeech he hardly eſcaped with his life. To apply this, when you goe out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſervice, know nothing in the world can impede &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice you, but ſinne, that you may keep your ſelues from evill, when the hoſt goes out to war. As when nature ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth with a diſeaſe, we wil not weaken it by more diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering our bodies, with what may wrong them, but will keep our ſelues within compaſſe, according to the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome rules of phyſick: ſo, when we ſtriue with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon adverſarie, we ought to keep our ſelues within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, according to the wholſome rules of <hi>Gods</hi> word. Some things there are, we ſhun, which would not do us halfe the harm, which yet we cannot ever avoid, as yll weather, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, fire, water. There be other things againe, to wit, our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> far worſe, &amp; more pernicious, which we may avoid, if we would.</p>
            <p>Secondly, remember how preſumptuouſly you ſinne, &amp; with an extream high hand; when you ſin now, when as you know you ought to ſin leaſt, not being ignorant what litle ſpace thou mayſt haue, or none at all, for grace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. If thou wilt put forth thine hand to evill, thou mayſt be dead, before thou ſhalt haue a heart to conſider, or time to ſay;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22, 34</note> 
               <hi>Lord, what haue I done? Ahab</hi> was ſlaine by a bow drawn at a venture, and ſmitten between the joints of his harnaſſe, when he litle thought of any ſuch thing. One
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15213:12"/>
               <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ananus</hi> (as <hi>Ioſephus makes mention</hi>) going about the walls, in the ſeige of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> with a ſtone ſhot from out an Engine, was ſodeinly killed. I note it, not as wonder, but giue inſtance of a thing, though ordinarie, yet worthie to be made uſe of.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, remember that if <hi>God</hi> were ſo offended with others, and a people as well beloved as we, for one or two evils, that he will not be well pleaſed with us, except we be more carefull then they were. He is angrie at ſin alike in al.</p>
            <p>Fourthly; remember what an honour this will be to you, to keep your ſelues from evill, when you haue the greateſt occaſions to run into evill. You muſt not thinke to make that an excuſe; who can in a <hi>leager</hi> keep himſelf from the common evils? I confeſſe it is hard; but ſo much the rather ſhouldſt thou keep thy ſelf from doing evill, if thou reſpect thine own honour, which then is ſeen moſt, when the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to haue been wicked, were not the leaſt. It is a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie, of the greater meaſure of grace in thee.</p>
            <p>Fiftly; remember to keep thy ſelf from evill abroad, and thou wilt with leſſe difficultie do it at home, that ſo both abroad and at home, it may be well with thee, and <hi>God</hi> may bleſſe thee.</p>
            <p>Laſtly; remember that <hi>one thing is neceſsarie,</hi> thy calling, thy employment,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.</note> which for the moſt part ſhould ſo take up thy thoughts, that thou ſhouldſt not haue time to doe evill. <hi>Obj.</hi> But muſt we haue no time to recreate our ſelus?
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, but not with ſin. He that ſaith there is a time for all things under the ſunne <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> doth ſpeak of no time allotted for ſin, becauſe ſinne muſt be done at no time. He devideth time between ſundrie ſorts of things, but he devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth none between good employment, and evill practiſe. To ſhew, that we ſhould be alwaies doing ſomewhat, where of ſome good may come, never doing any thing, which is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15213:13"/>of a nature evill in it ſelf, or of evill conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Keep thee,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) from evill, <hi>when the hoſt goes forth.</hi> Firſt, he ſpake of the <hi>generall</hi> bodie, then of the <hi>particular.</hi> The <hi>particular</hi> leſſe carefull of himſelf, to keep himſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evill, but giving libertie to himſelf, draweth on the <hi>general.</hi> Sin is of a ſpreading nature: and when one goeth before, (like beaſts that leape over a pale into a corne field, or out of the parke) all follow. The prayer, <hi>Deliver us from evill,</hi> requires your diligence &amp; care, not to run into evill. Who will madly run into a ditch or well, and yet ſay, <hi>deliver us from evill?</hi> We muſt thinke <hi>ſinne</hi> to be to us, as the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit to <hi>Adam,</hi> which he might not eat of, upon pain of death. We muſt let <hi>evill</hi> be to us, as the <hi>hony</hi> to them 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. which <hi>Saul</hi> too ſtrictly forbad his <hi>ſouldiers</hi> to meddle withall. <hi>Sinne</hi> muſt be to us, as the wine to the <hi>Rechabites,</hi> abominable to ſip of. Yea, we muſt keep our ſelues, &amp; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one his brother, as near as is poſſible, for that ſinn we may keepe others from, and do not, becommeth our ſinne. The <hi>Apostle</hi> bids us, not to partake in other mens ſinns: then do we partake in other mens ſinnes, not onely, when we joyne with them, but when we doe not, (if it lye in us) hinder them from evill. And the evill which any doe, by our connivence, ſhall trouble us, as well as them, perhaps more. And ſuch as are in place muſt watch &amp; keep others from evill, as much as in them is, (and much is in them to do, a great deale more then they do) viſit their unlawfull haunts, and haue a vigilant eye, to them. And one another muſt we keep by good counſell, by forbearing to joine in evill, and by diſcovering intended evill. But eſpecially, let everie man keepe himſelf, leaſt we be exemplarie to others in evill, &amp; ſith a mans own good, ſhould chiefly be tendred by himſelf. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4, 4, 5. <hi>This is the will of God, euen your ſanctification, that ye ſhould abſtaine from fornication. &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15213:13"/>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5, 22. <hi>Abstein from all appearance of evill.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 9. <hi>I beſeech you as pilgrims and ſtrangers, absteyn from fleſhly luſts.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5, 22. <hi>Keepe thy ſelf pure,</hi> and in another place, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4, 16. <hi>Take heede unto thy ſelf. Iam.</hi> 1. to keep himſelf, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted of the world,</hi> is <hi>pure religion. Iude</hi> 23. <hi>hating euen the garment ſpotted with the fleſh.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. <hi>touch no unclean thing.</hi> hold all ſin for unclean, to keep thy ſelf from it.</p>
            <p>And that we may do thus the better, conſider briefly, what <hi>meanes</hi> may be uſed by us. The <hi>means</hi> may be reduced to this method and order: viz. they are either <hi>generall</hi> or <hi>ſpeciall.</hi> Of the former ſort, is to gird to ones ſelf the whole <hi>armour of God. Eph.</hi> 6, 14. And of that armour, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the ſword, which is the <hi>word of God,</hi> and ſpecially ſuch places of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as this, and the like before. And let thy heart, be the ſheath of this ſpirituall ſword. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119, 11. <hi>I haue hid thy word within my heart, that I might not ſinne againſt thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, thinke of <hi>prayer,</hi> which though it be no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per piece of that armour, yet neceſſarily belongs thereunto. With prayer join vowes, from a reſolved ſpirit. Pray, I ſay, to <hi>God,</hi> to keepe thee, as the prophet <hi>Ier.</hi> 17, 14. to <hi>God</hi> do thou pray for his grace, <hi>The Lord is faithfull, who ſhall ſtabliſh you, &amp; keep you from evill.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3, 3. And his grace is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 5. <hi>to guard thee.</hi> Forget not <hi>vowes,</hi> which is <hi>the bond of the ſoule. Num.</hi> 30, 3. And the Greek word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is both a <hi>prayer,</hi> and a <hi>vow</hi> in ſenſe, and we ſhall do well to joyne them together in <hi>practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the latter ſort of means, to wit, the <hi>particular,</hi> are theſe four, which follow. The firſt is, to look to the heart, and to the verie firſt riſings of evill there. The heart is the fountain. Other evils lye without you, but the evils of ſin lye within you, in Ambuſcado, euen in our verie hearts. <hi>Salomons</hi> counſel is, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4. <hi>Aboue all keepings keep thy heart.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15213:14"/>Let not thy heart conſent, nor giue it leaue, to thinke of evill, and thy hand ſhall never act any unworthy thing.</p>
            <p>Secondly; keep from outward occaſions, and make a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with thine eyes. And if thou wilt indeed keep thee from wickednes, keep thee from <hi>wicked companie. Prov.</hi> 1, 10. If thou be a child of wiſdome, heare the wholeſome counſel of thy mother, ſaying: <hi>My ſon, if ſinners intice thee, conſent thou not.</hi> If ſtill they urge thee (as ſin is impudent, and importunate, and will hardly be ſaid nay) &amp; ſay <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>Come with us, let us lay wait for blood, &amp;c. ver.</hi> 14. <hi>Cast in thy lot among us, let us all haue one purſe.</hi> My ſonne, <hi>walke not thou in the way with them, refraine thy foot from their path: for their feete runne to evill. &amp;c.</hi> There is no more diueliſh oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to all wickednes, then wicked &amp; vicious company.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, betake thy ſelf to the oppoſite good thing, or buſie thy ſelf in wel-doing, about thy calling, <hi>generall,</hi> as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> in prayer, in reading profitable books, <hi>divine</hi> or <hi>politique</hi> when thy leaſure ſerues thee, not in thoſe bawdy and wicked Playbooks, or <hi>Amorous</hi> toyes, the ſcumme and ſcurf of ſcald and ſcabby heads, as one calleth them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Particular,</hi> in the place that thou art in. And ſomtimes unbend thy ſelf thou mayſt to the moderate exerciſe of ſome lawfull recreation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly; labour for a greater meaſure of <hi>Gods</hi> fear. What is the reaſon we are ſo headlong in ſin, and ſo voide of all care, but the want of this grace? There is a ſlaviſh fear, and a fear filiall: if it be but from a ſlaviſh fear that thou fears to do evill, to avoid puniſhment, which will certainly follow thy ſin (<hi>for be ſure thy ſinne will finde thee out. Num.</hi> 32, 23. And <hi>the stipend of ſin is death. Rom.</hi> 6, 23. And <hi>if you liue in the works of the fleſh you ſhall dye. Rom.</hi> 8, 14.) euen that is ſomewhat, and ſhall leſſen thy puniſhment in hell. If it be from a filiall fear and reſpect, that withholds thee, it is ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15213:14"/>much the better, that like a childe, the loue of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, mixt with an awfull fear of his diſpleaſure, reſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thee. Were ſuch a fear, or any feare of <hi>God</hi> before our eyes, &amp; in our hearts, it would keep us from a great deale of ſin. It would tye our tongues from lyings, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and falſe <hi>accuſations,</hi> from hideous <hi>blaſphemies,</hi> which flye up &amp; down among you, from <hi>filthie-ſpeaking.</hi> Would binde our hands from revenge, &amp; ſhackle our feet, from running to any evill whatſoever. But this fear of <hi>God</hi> being away, (as it is from the moſt) we make no ſcruple, no conſcience, no matter of any wicked thing or word. If thou hadſt the fear of that glorious <hi>God,</hi> whoſe order this is, which is here giuen, thou wouldſt not dare to put forth thy hand to evill. Compare <hi>Mal.</hi> 3, 5. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 3, 14-18. and there may be ſeene that the want of Gods fear, is the cauſe why me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare do any wickednes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be noted here, is, that this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition is <hi>abſolute,</hi> and <hi>univerſall, to forbeare all evill. Then keep thee from everie wicked thing,</hi> or, <hi>from all. Obſerv. 2.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> Men muſt keep themſelues from all and everie evill, when the hoſt goeth forth &amp;c.</hi> There is a twofold prohibition from evill, as one ſheweth. The one <hi>abſolute,</hi> and ſimple: as to blaſpheme, to lye, which are directly againſt <hi>Gods</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which we may in no wiſe doe, upon any termes whatſoever. The other reſpectiue; as not to kill, work on the Sabboth, plunder, burne, and fire houſes, and corne, which things <hi>God</hi> himſelf doth ſometime, and is lawfull to be done againſt an enimie. The evill we are here forbidden, is of the former nature, in manners and behaviour, from all which we are to abſteine.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Adam</hi> was in <hi>paradiſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen</hi> 2, 16, 17.</note> God</hi> gaue him the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all trees in the garden, except the tree in the midſt of the ſame, which he enjoyned him not to touch. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15213:15"/>him all trees, exempting him of one. But in this caſe, <hi>God</hi> allowes no tree of ſin to be approached unto: he hath exempted us from everie one. <hi>Lev. 18, 24. Defile not your ſelues in any of theſe things.</hi> and <hi>2 Cor. 13, 7. I pray God</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>that ye do no evill, not that ye ſhould appeare approved, but that ye ſhould do that which is honest. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is; <hi>Gods</hi> hatred, &amp; minde, doth go againſt evill univerſally; all as well as any; who therefore hath forbidden all evill in the morall Law. And in the 14 v. here following, <hi>God</hi> muſt not ſe any unclea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes in them.</p>
            <p>Secondly; Conſcience, where it is of evill, as it is evil, forbeareth one as well as another, everie one, as well as any one: for conſcience is <hi>univerſall</hi> in good or evill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſect.</hi> Hence then you ſee, that we would not haue you more preciſe and ſcrupulous in your cariage, and converſation among men, then <hi>Gods</hi> word would haue you; wherein you ſee no diſpenſation, for any wicked thing. The Word whereby you muſt be judged at the <hi>laſt day.</hi> We dare giue you no more libertie, then that doth; and wiſh, that you would take no more.</p>
            <p>But let us enquire, what evils ſpecially of all evils, we are to forbeare. And ſome <hi>ſpecies</hi> and <hi>particulars</hi> contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under this <hi>generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt; thou muſt keepe thee from thoſe evils in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular which <hi>Gods</hi> word doth mention to be evils, and wicked things, more ſpecially, in his ſight; as namely: <hi>Violence,</hi> to thoſe we ought to offer no <hi>violence</hi> unto. See theſe places: <hi>Deut.</hi> 2, 4. a ſtrict command. <hi>And command thou the people ſaying; ye are to paſſe through the coast of your brethren, &amp;c. take good heed unto your ſelues, meddle not with them. Deut. 20.19. God would not ſuffer them to doe violence to the trees. Luke 3.14. Doe violence to no man, &amp;c. Pſal. 62, 10. Davids</hi> ſpeech to his <hi>Souldiers; Trust not in oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15213:15"/>become not vaine in robberie.</hi> This is one of that all, which we are forbidden, and yet too rife among us, and too commonly practiſed by us.</p>
            <p>Another is <hi>fornication</hi> or <hi>adulterie.</hi> See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.4. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> young men muſt keep them ſelues from women.
<note place="margin">Which (as it ſeemeth (reſpec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted not ſo much the holy bread in that place ſpoken of as their iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid in the warrs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their own women.</note> and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11, 11. <hi>Vriah</hi> alſo ſpeaks againſt lying with his own wife at that time, much leſſe would he haue his <hi>whoore</hi> by him, at any time.</p>
            <p>Another wicked thing is; <hi>abuſe of the creatures</hi> in drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe and ryot: which exceſſe in a campe, is contrarie to that, required in thoſe that goe a warfare. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9, 25. <hi>Everie man that ſtriveth for the masterie is temperate in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another wicked thing; is <hi>murmuring</hi> and <hi>mutining</hi> in the Campe. See this taken notice of in thoſe rebels <hi>Num.</hi> 16, 1, 2, 3, 11. which was to be puniſhed with death. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1, 18.</p>
            <p>In a word; <hi>evill ſpeaking</hi> is wicked. And that is under this <hi>Hebrew</hi> word, forbidden in the text, which ſignifieth <hi>word,</hi> as well as <hi>thing; keepe thee from everie evill word,</hi> as well as <hi>keepe thee from everie wicked thing.</hi> See <hi>Lev.</hi> 24, 11, 14. <hi>he that blaſpheamed</hi> (or, as the word ſignifieth, that pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced through) <hi>the Lord his name, all the Congregation stoned him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, theſe be ſpecially the evils, when the hoſt goeth forth we are to keep our ſelues from. And whatſoever els is wicked: and thinke no evill to be too little to be eyed. Conſider him <hi>Num.</hi> 15, 32. that having gathered ſticks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sabaoth day, he muſt be ſtoned without the Camp,</p>
            <p>Secondly; thou muſt keep thy ſelf, as from everie evill &amp; wicked thing, ſo from <hi>thy particular evill;</hi> which is, the evil of ſinn thou art moſt by nature prone unto. <hi>David</hi> calleth it, his <hi>iniquitie. Pſal.</hi> 18, 24. <hi>I will keepe my ſelfe from mine
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15213:16"/>iniquitie.</hi> As everie wiſe and carefull man will looke moſt to that humour, which is moſt naturally predominant in him, and correct it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39, 1. <hi>I ſayd, I will take heed to my wayes:</hi> and becauſe he might ſooneſt do amiſſe with his tongue, he would ſo take heed to his wayes, that he would not offend with his tongue, which he moſt feared, it ſemes: <hi>I will keepe my mouth with a bridle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſect.</hi> 2. Therefore againe, in caſe we haue fayled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this caveat, &amp; haue done any evill, our hearts ſhould ſmite us, for as much as we haue ſinned againſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe charge of <hi>Gods</hi> word. And this is a ſigne of true grace, and of <hi>Gods</hi> good <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and of a tender conſcience in a man, to feele the evill he hath done. A man of a tender ſtomack, or, who hath this or that grief about him, if he venter to eat or drinke of a thing that is hurtfull, he ſhall preſently hear of it, in that part yll affected: ſo, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hath a true conſcience of all evill, having unhappily done any, drawn away of his own luſt, and entiſed; will ſoone complaine thereof. <hi>David,</hi> when he had ſtretched out his hand againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> the Lords anointed, the fact did not a little perplex him.</p>
            <p>And thus much of this Caveat giuen the people, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare evill, and everie wicked thing, when the <hi>hoſt</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is gone forth againſt the enimie.</p>
            <p>Now it followeth, that we conſider the words of the 14 verſe. <hi>For the Lord thy God walketh in the mids of thy Campe, to deliver thee, and to giue up thine enimies before thee: therefore ſhall thy Campe be holy, that he ſee no uncleannes in thee, and turne away from thee.</hi> Which words, follow as a reaſon of the former, why they muſt doe no wicked thing in the hoſt. The <hi>argument</hi> hath two things in it, to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally noted:</p>
            <p>Firſt, a <hi>propoſition,</hi> concerning <hi>Gods</hi> preſence among
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15213:16"/>them: <hi>For the Lord thy God walketh in the mids of the Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly; the <hi>conſequence</hi> or <hi>concluſion: Therefore ſhall thy Campe be holy. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, is amplified from the finall cauſe of <hi>Gods</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence among them; which is, <hi>to deliver them, and to giue up their enimies before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord thy God.]</hi> The <hi>Chalde</hi> applieth it to the <hi>Divine Majeſtie,</hi> or <hi>preſence;</hi> ſo called, from <hi>dwelling,</hi> and fitly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who dwelt among us, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the auncient <hi>Hebrewes</hi> meant it of the <hi>Meſsias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walketh] mithallech,</hi> the <hi>forme</hi> of the word, noteth the frequencie of the action, walking up and down, and as it were, to and fro, here and there, continually, like a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>inſpectour</hi> or <hi>overſeer. In the midſt]</hi> that is, among or within the Campe, as the <hi>parallell</hi> phraſe elſewhere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens; not preciſely reſpecting the midſt, the heart, but the Campe <hi>generally.</hi> See <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.9.3, 3. and 23, 6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24, 3. for the meaning of this phraſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>obſervation is;</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> that <hi>God hath his walke among us, where we are encamped againſt his and our enimies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 20 chapter he is ſaid, to be with them, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie them in their wars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Levit.</hi> 26, 11, 12. <hi>I will ſet my tabernacle among you, and my ſoule ſhall not abhorre you. And, I will walke among you.</hi> Chald. <hi>My</hi> Word <hi>ſhall walke among you.</hi> Compare it with <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1, 1.) and will be your <hi>God,</hi> and you ſhall be my people. <hi>Gods</hi> walke is everie where, <hi>He</hi> hath his paths in the ſea, and ſtrideth over the land. But, he is ſpecially ſaid, to be in ſome places. As <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> lodged among his people <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 8, 9. ſo, <hi>God</hi> encamps among his, and lodgeth in the midſt of them, <hi>as a King in his armie. Iob</hi> 29, 25. <hi>Iob</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares himſelfe in the dayes of old, ſpeaking how it was wont to be with him in elder times, the years of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15213:17"/>when the light of <hi>God</hi> ſhined upon his tabernacle, ſayth, <hi>he ſate chiefe in the gates, as a King in the armie. God</hi> walketh in the mids of his Camps, as a <hi>King</hi> in the armie, as the mightie <hi>Lord Generall,</hi> and <hi>Lord of hoſts</hi> and armies, like <hi>a man of warre. Exod.</hi> 15, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſect.</hi> 1. Doth the <hi>Lord God</hi> walke in the mids of our Camps? then ſhould we take him in. Doth he walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, as it were, and ſhall we let him alone, and not ſeeke to enjoy him? oh, let him haue a roome in your hearts, in your tents and Cabins, he knocks, and would enter in to you, if you will open unto him. Yet I muſt tell you, <hi>God</hi> will not goe in to all. He will abhor to goe into <hi>Achans</hi> tent, for there lyeth the <hi>accurſed thing.</hi> In the 16 of <hi>Num.</hi> 26 ver. they are bid to depart the tents of the wicked; and will God himſelfe goe in to them? <hi>He</hi> will not goe into theſe filthie places, that are neſts, and cages of uncleane birds, and where no goodnes, no holynes dwelleth, no prayer, nor prayſing of him, no reading of his word, nor feare of his majeſtie reſideth: nothing but lewdnes, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes, oaths, and all manner of impietie. Nay, <hi>God</hi> will turne away from ſuch, as followeth here in the words. If thy tent be a tent of wickednes and ſinne, <hi>God</hi> is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, and will ſcatter fire, and burne up the tents of wickednes, and the wicked in them. <hi>Purge out therefore the old leaven,</hi> that the <hi>Lord</hi> may delight to come into us. But as there was no roome for Chriſt in the Inne: ſo I doubt me, there is litle roome for <hi>God,</hi> in the tents and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of many of us. He walketh in the midſt of us, to ſee who will giue him the beſt corner of his heart, the beſt entertainment in his tent. If ſome great man of worth and preſence ſhould make his walke continually among us, if we thought, he would vouchſafe to come in unto us, we would make him the beſt welcome we could: but there
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15213:17"/>is not the meaneſt of us, if by prayer we invite <hi>God</hi> unto us, though our tents be never ſo poore, to whom he will not eaſily vouchſafe to come. But we unkindely neglect him, being naturally ſtrangers unto him <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. Yet as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the <hi>Canticles</hi> tooke hold of <hi>Christ,</hi> and pulled him in: ſo take thou hold on <hi>God,</hi> and draw him in to thee. But, <hi>there is no man, that calleth upon thy name, and that stirreth up himſelfe to take hould of thee:</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> complains <hi>Ieſ.</hi> 64. ſpeaking of <hi>God. Acquaint now thy ſelf with him, and be at peace, thereby good ſhall come unto thee, put away iniquitie far from thy tabernacle. Iob</hi> 22.21.</p>
            <p>Secondly; Is <hi>God</hi> walking among us? therefore, we haue, and ſee the more reaſon to keepe our ſelues from everie wicked thing, as before we heard. A moſt effectual <hi>argument</hi> muſt this needs be, to conſider him, who is invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and hath his walke in the midſt of our Campe, for everie man to binde himſelf to the good behaviour. As a <hi>King</hi> hath many times, his ſecret unknown pacings, inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble walkings among his ſubjects, and heareth all that they ſay, beholds all that they doe, and ſometimes, heares them ſpeake of things farre unmeete for them to intereſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in; poſſibly ſpeaking treaſon, againſt his crown and dignitie, reviling his perſon, diſgracing him, or ſome of his, depraving his government, his actions or doings. And all this, with a ſilent eare paſſing it by, or els takes hold of them in the manner. Euen ſo doth <hi>God</hi> walke in the mids of us, we ſee him not, a cloud covering him, a Canopy overſhadowing him and his brightneſſe, leaſt we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by him, who ſeeth and heareth, though we thinke not.</p>
            <p>And, as in the third of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> he was walking in the mids of the garden, when <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> had hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and called unto them: ſo can he call unto us, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15213:18"/>we are about, whenſoever we ſpeake, or do amiſſe, as he called ſodeinly to them three for ſpeaking evill of Moſes <hi>Num.</hi> 12, 1, 2, 4. And can he chuſe but heare us blaſpheaming his name, and toſſing his glorious <hi>attributes</hi> up and down, in our unſanctified mouths? Shall not he, who walketh in the midſt of us heare our diſgracing his <hi>meſsengers,</hi> reviling his <hi>ordinances?</hi> Can he chuſe but ſee our <hi>miſ-carriage</hi> and <hi>miſbehaviour</hi> toward him, and one toward another? Cannot he ſee one reeling in his filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ryot and exceſſe, in his drinke and vomit; another ſmiting with the fiſt of wickednes? another <hi>idle,</hi> negligent in his ſervice, or ſinfully employed? <hi>Thou giveſt thy mouth to evill, and thy tongue frameth deceit. Thou ſittest and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt againſt thy brother, and ſlandreſt thine owne mothers ſonne. Theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence, thou thoughteſt that I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf: but I will reproue thee, and ſet them in order before thee. Pſal.</hi> 50, 19. <hi>For the wayes of man are before the eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his goings. Prov.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Mine eyes are upon all their wayes, they are not hid from my face, nor is their iniquitie hidde from mine eyes. Ier.</hi> 16.17. The greateſt incentuie to all good comportment and carriage, is this; to remember, <hi>God</hi> is walking before us. And, <hi>he which made the eyes ſhall not he ſee? he that made the eare ſhall not he heare? Pſal.</hi> 94. If thy <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Generall</hi> were walking in the midſt of us wouldſt thou dare to doe what thou doeſt, for evill, when thou dreameſt, he is not neare thee? <hi>Offer this</hi> (ſayth <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie</hi>) <hi>unto thy Prince.</hi> So, doe that which thou ſhouldſt not do, before thy Prince, and ſee how he will take it at thy hands. And, ſhall the glorious <hi>God, of pure eyes</hi> walke up and down among us, and we boldly and preſumptuouſly ſinne againſt him, juſt before him? oh, ſet <hi>God</hi> before you. But, ſayth <hi>David</hi> of the wicked, <hi>God is not in all their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15213:18"/>thoughts.</hi> Let his <hi>reſpect</hi> rule and ſway, in the hearts of us all. <hi>Stand in awe therefore, and ſinne not. Pſalm.</hi> 4, 4. He ſhall not neede to come downe (as <hi>according to men</hi> is ſayd of him) now, and ſee whether we haue done altogether af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the crye of our ſinnes, and if not, that he may know. Wherefore, doth the <hi>Lord</hi> walk in the midſt of our waies, of our walkes, of our Camps? what ſhould we be carefull to doe then? but, to take heede to our wayes and walkes, that they be not to evill, but to walke before him, and be upright, as he ſpake to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.1. and walke humbly with our <hi>God: Mich.</hi> 7. <hi>What doeth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to ſhew mercie, &amp;c. and to walke hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God?</hi> Let us neither doe nor ſpeake any more, then what we durſt doe or ſpeak before the <hi>Lord,</hi> who walketh in the midſt of our Camps.</p>
            <p>Conſect. 3. Then here may we performe ſervice to him, euen in our Camps, where he is, where he treadeth. Tyed we are not to any remote place, to goe and worſhip the Lord, or if we would enquire at <hi>God.</hi> His <hi>arke</hi> in the mids of them 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.5.6. was a <hi>Symbolicall</hi> ſigne of his preſence among them. And that he who <hi>walketh in the midſt of the ſeuen golden Candleſticks,</hi> walded alſo,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.</note> in the mids of their armies. Here may we, here ought we, to erect and ſet up his worſhip. For this cauſe we finde the <hi>Levites</hi> were diſperſed among their Camps, and quarters, as we may read in <hi>Numbers</hi> and <hi>Ioſhuah.</hi> And when <hi>Saul</hi> was in the field, the <hi>Lords Prieſt</hi> was with him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.3. And if indeed the <hi>Lord</hi> walk in the mids of our Camps, let him haue his <hi>Sabaoths</hi> ſanctified, and thoſe dueties performed, which he expecteth from us. Let him haue his <hi>morning,</hi> and <hi>euening ſacrifices</hi> among us. Oh, let his walks ſmell &amp; ſavour with the reake of all good things done to him. And that he may delight to be among us, let us, oh let us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15213:19"/>his waies with the odoriferous incenſe of prayer and praiſe, and ſtrew his walks with the ſweete ſpices of fayth and repentance, as with roſes and lillies.</p>
            <p>This firſt part is illuſtrated, from the end of his walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the midſt of our Camps: Namely, <hi>to deliver thee from thine enimies,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vnde Apollinis</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>quod ambiguis ambagibus, reſponſa conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentibus daret.</hi>
                  </note> and to giue up thine enimies before thee. Gods</hi> oracles are plaine, and labour with no ambiguities, like thoſe of <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> and <hi>Craeſus,</hi> whereof no certaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning could be gathered, whereupon to go boldly forth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>to giue up thine enimies before thee]</hi> to deliver before, here, and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.36. is to deliver unto. Conferre <hi>Deut,</hi> 7, 2. with 23. as if he ſhould haue ſaid. In thy Campe doth the <hi>Lord</hi> thy <hi>God</hi> abide, there doth he walke purpoſely, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee from thine enimies, and to deliver thine enimies unto thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervat.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> 2. <hi>Gods walke, and preſence amids our Camps, is with a purpoſe to doe us all good, to keepe us from our enimies, and to giue us power over them.</hi> Not onely, to deliver us from them, that they put us not to the worſe, but to giue them into our hands. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.4. <hi>The Lord your God is he that goeth with you, to fight for you againſt your enimies to ſaue you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is: firſt, becauſe his people haue the right &amp; the cauſe. See 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8, 45. And the <hi>Lord</hi> is bound after a ſort, to mainteine their judgment, their <hi>right</hi> or <hi>cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the warre is his. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20, 15. <hi>the battail is not yours, but Gods.</hi> And the cauſe is the <hi>Lords</hi> own <hi>Pſa.</hi> 74.22. And the <hi>Lord</hi> is their <hi>Capteine.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13, 12. And, he hath taken them on, who are therefore his armies and troopes, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.26.45. So that his honour lyeth upon it, and is intereſſed in it, in regard of the enimie, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe will blaſpheame, if he ſaue not his people, they will inſult. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32, 27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79, 4. Againe in regard of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15213:19"/>his people, they cannot glorifie him, as were meet they ſhould. <hi>Pſal. 50, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God will make his people revenge the <hi>quarrell</hi> of his Covenant upon them.</p>
            <p>This ſets before us an argument of <hi>Gods</hi> loue &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and care for his, in being thus propitious to them in their wars, as to be among them, for ſo gracious an end. Here ſome may object; how is it then,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> they are ſo often delivered, not <hi>from,</hi> but <hi>to</hi> their enimies, &amp; in ſtead of having their <hi>enimies,</hi> their <hi>enimies</hi> haue them: which <hi>Iſrael</hi> oftentimes had experience of between <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt</hi> and <hi>Canaan,</hi> and afterward. See <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7. They ſmote <hi>Iſraell</hi> euen unto <hi>Shebarim,</hi> a place ſo called, from the mightie breach, which was made at that time. So in the 20 of <hi>Iudges</hi> the <hi>Beniamites</hi> ſmote the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> once and againe: and many times the people of <hi>God</hi> are put to the worſe. To which I anſwer two waies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that ſo it may be for a time,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> but at the laſt <hi>God</hi> will make this good. Marke then the end, ſee what he hath done at the ſecond, third or fourth bout, his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall carrie it away at length, and haue the day. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that at any time it falleth out otherwiſe then this ſeemes to promiſe them, is by <hi>accident</hi> for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſins. And ſo we muſt underſtand this with limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and qualified with this condition: <hi>if that we be not in fault God</hi> is ever readie to help us and ſtand by us, ever prone and forward for our deliverance and victorie. When it is not according to this, the fault is in our ſelues. <hi>Oh that my people had hearkened unto me, and would haue walked in my wayes I ſhould ſoone haue ſubdued their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and turned my hand againſt their adverſaries. The ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Lord ſhould ſoone haue ſubmitted themſelves unto him, but their time ſhould haue endured for ever. Pſal.</hi> 81, 13.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15213:20"/>Would we approue our waies unto <hi>God,</hi> among us he would walke to deliver us from our enimies, and them to us; but, if we will not, but breake out to everie wicked thing, againſt his expreſſe word, among us he will be, but in judgment, to deliver us to our adverſaries, and to the will of thoſe that hate us. <hi>If they ſinne againſt thee, and thou be angrie with them</hi> (ſayth <hi>Salomon</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46.) <hi>and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them to the Enimie, &amp;c.</hi> Where we ſee, it is <hi>ſinne</hi> that makes <hi>Gods</hi> preſence fruitleſſe, and booteleſſe to us for good. It is not becauſe the <hi>Lord,</hi> who is <hi>armipotent,</hi> could not alwaies deliver us from our enimies, and giue them to us; but becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> will trie us, and for that we proue him with our ſinnes. Or, <hi>Either</hi> we uſe not the meanes God would haue us uſe, and then <hi>God</hi> will not deliver us, who ordinarily, <hi>will not ſaue his people without his people,</hi> that is, without their diligence. Though the meanes and our induſtrie be nothing without God, yet is it his pleaſure, we ſhould not neglect them, which when we doe, he will be nothing to us. He will haue us up, and be doing, and leaue him to be at our Elbowes, to fall on and ſecond us. Or ſecondly, we truſt too much to the means, our hearts being too much ſet upon them, and hanging after them. We are apt, to thinke of our own ſtrength and policie, and not to regard God, whoſe power and providence it muſt be to deliver us from our enimies, &amp; them to us. Whence many a day is loſt, and faire exploit vaniſht, many an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious aſſault made upon us, to our juſt reproach.</p>
            <p>Secondly; we muſt then expect this in fayth, and in the apprehention of God, and his <hi>divine</hi> preſence among us, looke to be delivered from our enimies, and not onely that, but haue them fairly delivered unto us, be they never ſo many, ſo mightie, and warlike a nation. If God were in the midſt of their Camp, for this end, in mercie to reſcue
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15213:20"/>them, and to giue up thoſe <hi>miſcreants</hi> their enimies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, ſhould not this greatly encourage them, in hope of victorie? But, this is a fruit of fayth in <hi>God, wherefore, looke unto me, and be ye ſaved, oh all the ends of the earth. Ieſ.</hi> 45, 22.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the firſt branch of theſe words: <hi>The propoſition, touching Gods preſence among them,</hi> &amp; walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Camps to cover their heads.</p>
            <p>The ſecond branch of theſe words, is the concluſion or conſequence, wherein note; firſt, an <hi>order:</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a <hi>reaſon</hi> of that order.</p>
            <p>The <hi>order</hi> is layd downe <hi>two wayes, affirmatiuely,</hi> or <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiuely,</hi> touching holynes required: <hi>Therefore ſhall thy Campe be holy. Negatiuely</hi> or <hi>privatiuely,</hi> againſt unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>That he ſee no uncleannes in thee.</hi> The <hi>reaſon</hi> of the <hi>order,</hi> is from the dangerous effect of this; <hi>Gods turning away from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue heard <hi>Moſes</hi> telling them of <hi>Gods</hi> preſence with them, now we ſhall ſee what ought to follow thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>therefore the Camp muſt not be unclean.</hi> Where he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the <hi>place,</hi> and of the <hi>men</hi> likewiſe, and the <hi>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> of the one, implies the <hi>puritie</hi> of the other. Of the <hi>place,</hi> their <hi>Campground</hi> muſt be holy. There was a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>ſanctitie: Ceremoniall</hi> and <hi>Morall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The earth they lay upon muſt be <hi>ceremonially</hi> cleane: Alſo their men, their perſons muſt be morally <hi>holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note further, that holynes may be eyther <hi>faederall,</hi> or <hi>practicall. Faederally</hi> and by <hi>league,</hi> they were a holy people. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7, 6. by dedication holy; here is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that they be <hi>practically</hi> holy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv. 3. Foraſmuch as God is among us,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>3</label> we muſt all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be holy. God would haue our Camps and leagers holy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15213:21"/>Camps, and holy leagers.</hi> Oh (ſayth <hi>Moſes</hi>) if the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>God</hi> be among us, our Camps and tents ſhould be holy. But the Lord is among us, in the mids of us. Therefore ſhall your Camp be holy. According to that, <hi>Lev.</hi> 20, 7. <hi>Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſie your ſelues, and be ye holy, for I the Lord your God am holy.</hi> Where we haue a precept to be <hi>holy,</hi> and a reaſon, <hi>the Lord our God is holy.</hi> A <hi>Campe of Saints</hi> is mentioned <hi>Revel.</hi> 20, 9. <hi>It becometh all the Lords people to be holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>as he is holy. This is the will of God, your ſanctification, that everie one of you ſhould know how to poſseſſe his veſsell in ſanctification, and in honour. God</hi> would haue his people delight in holynes, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe doeth. Holy they muſt be in all things, in their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies and meetings, of what ſort, or for what end ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and holy in their Camps and wars.</p>
            <p>This was figuratiuely enjoyned: firſt, in their <hi>waſhings verſe</hi> 11. When the euening commeth on, he ſhall waſh himſelf, to wit, any man that was not cleane, by any <hi>noc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnall pollution,</hi> he muſt goe out of the Campe, and not come within the Camp, till he was cleanſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly; by burying their <hi>excrements, verſe</hi> 12. <hi>Thou ſhalt haue a place without the Campe, whither thou ſhalt goe forth abroad, and thou ſhalt haue a paddle upon thy weapon, and it ſhall be, when thou wilt eaſe thy ſelfe abroad, thou ſhalt digge therewith, and ſhalt turne back and cover that which cometh from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſons</hi> for holynes in our Camps. The firſt reaſon is; becauſe <hi>God</hi> can preſently ſmell out any unholynes, who is of perfect ſight,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt he ſee</hi> (ſayth <hi>Moſes) uncleannes in thee.</hi> As who ſhould ſay, <hi>God</hi> will quickly ſpye it out, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pure eyes, nothing can hide it from him. And of perfect ſent, if I may ſo ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Secondly; that holynes may diſtinguiſh betweene our Enimies and us, without which we differ not from them,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15213:21"/>they from us. For men they are as well as we, ſuch war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like furniture they haue as we. And this ſhall difference more then any diſtance of place, or other qualities. Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie doeth in a manner, make a conſimilitude betweene them and us. See <hi>Ieſ.</hi> 1, 10. they are called rulers of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and people of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> becauſe though by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and profeſſion, they were Iewes, and the people of <hi>God,</hi> yet in manners they were like <hi>Sodome</hi> and her <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> So <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16, 3.45, 46. <hi>Thy birth and thy nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is of the land of Canaan: thy father was an Ammonite, and thy mother an Hittite.</hi> So that the impuritie of thoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which they declared in their works, made them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together like them. In this ſenſe <hi>Saul</hi> was a <hi>Cuſhite Pſal.</hi> 7. So that, nothing will diſtinguiſh us from our enimies, but holyneſſe onely, for want whereof, take away the title of <hi>Gods</hi> people, we are as they are. And, our Camps, if ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes reigne not in them, are not the Camps of <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but of <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> of <hi>Sodomites,</hi> of <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; For our Camps and armies to be holy, would make our enimies bluſh and be aſhamed; yea, would da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle their ſight to looke at us, would throw them to the ground, and make them fall backward, as the <hi>Souldiers</hi> did, when they came to apprehend <hi>Christ, Iohn</hi> 18, 6. The verie holynes of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Campe, would confound the <hi>armies of the Aliens. Holynes</hi> would driue our enimies from us. All <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>ſinners</hi> ſinke, and fall at the preſence of <hi>holynes.</hi> The ſame excellencie in <hi>God,</hi> is that which ſcarres all from comming neare unto him, who dwelleth in that <hi>light</hi> of holynes, <hi>which none can attaine unto:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6, 16.</note> in ſo much that <hi>Ieſay</hi> cryed out, <hi>he was undone, chap.</hi> 6, 3, 5. becauſe of his owne uncleanneſſe, and that wonderfull holynes in <hi>God. Peter,</hi> in the ſenſe of his owne impuritie, bids <hi>Chriſt</hi> to depart from him, <hi>Luke</hi> 5, 8. or he muſt runne away
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15213:22"/>from <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Yea holynes in an <hi>Angell,</hi> which is but a ſparcle of <hi>Gods</hi> holynes, made them ſo affrighted <hi>Dan.</hi> 10, 7. and <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſo perplexed, he knew not what to doe. <hi>Luke</hi> 1, 12. And certainly, holynes in <hi>Gods</hi> people, which they haue by communication, and participation from <hi>God,</hi> is that, which if it were in a more excellent degree, would ſkarre their enimies, and make them ſhrinke before them. This <hi>Rom.</hi> 13, 13. is called their <hi>armour of light,</hi> which in truth ſo flaſheth in the ſore eyes of the world, and dazel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, that they are able to doe nothing againſt them who weare it. As ſinne and impuritie hath a ſecret kinde of force, whereby we are weakened, and doth fight againſt us; ſo holynes hath a ſecret vertue to worke as much for us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly; holynes is to be choſen for it ſelf, it is a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie ſo glorious. In regard of this, no queſtion, <hi>Balaam</hi> cryed out, when he viewed the Camps of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> ſaying; <hi>How goodly are thy tents, O Iacob, and thy tabernacles, O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. Num.</hi> 24, 5.</p>
            <p>Fiftly; everie place ſhould be ſuitable to the <hi>Majestie</hi> and ſacred nature of the <hi>perſon</hi> therein. Therefore, our Camps where <hi>God</hi> walketh, ſhould be holy: which to be is ſuiteable to his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and nature. If a King ſhould come and walke among us, there would be ſuch care to haue all things comely and pure: ſo, in that <hi>God</hi> hath his reſidence among us, his place muſt be holy. Yet cannot he contract any impuritie, be the place what it will be. As the <hi>ſunne</hi> ſhyning with his light into the moſt noyſome &amp; filthy vault, yet is free from impuritie notwithſtanding; no more is <hi>God</hi> defiled, by any the moſt noyſome place: yet he delights to finde his owne cleanneſſe, where he is pleaſed to come.</p>
            <p>What remaines then, but that we labour and ſtriue to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15213:22"/>be holy, to haue holy Campes, and holy leagers. It was propheſied <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.20. that on the <hi>bells</hi> of the horſes ſhould be written, <hi>Holynes to Iehovah.</hi> Meaning, that the warres, and Camps under the <hi>Goſpell</hi> ſhould be holy warres and holy Camps. The <hi>horſe</hi> is a warlike beaſt. See <hi>Iob</hi> 39. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21, 31. and by <hi>Synechdoche</hi> in that place of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, may comprehend other things belonging to the Campe. And when holynes is engrauen upon the horſe, what ſhould the Rider haue on him, but holynes alſo? That ſo our Camps and wars may be anſwerable to that the <hi>Lord</hi> requires here. <hi>Object.</hi> But, will ſome ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> is it poſſible for our <hi>leagers</hi> to be ſo? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is it poſſible?
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> why not? were it a thing impoſſible, <hi>God</hi> would not haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired it of them or us. Poſſible it is through grace, and the meanes conſcionably improved. And we ſee holynes in ſome, therefore I ſee not, but it may be more generall: which takes away the vaine <hi>objection</hi> of many, who thinke becauſe they are <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and follow the warrs, they haue nothing to do with <hi>holynes,</hi> ſuppoſing it ynough for <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> and others to be carefull for holynes. But, <hi>God</hi> would haue the Camp holy; now what is the Campe, but thoſe who make the Campe, which are <hi>Souldiers:</hi> wherefore <hi>Souldiers</hi> muſt not caſt off the care of holynes. This holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſtandeth in abſteyning from all evill, whereof before. Secondly, in doing the contrarie good: and the rule of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, is that of the <hi>Apoſtle, Phil.</hi> 4, 8. <hi>Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are just, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are louely, whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, thinke on theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>meanes</hi> requiſite toward a holy Campe, are ſpecially theſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt is; that everie man beginne with himſelf, to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15213:23"/>reforme himſelf. If everie man cleanſe his owne dore, we ſhall haue cleane ſtreets: ſo, would everie man cleanſe himſelf, we ſhould haue a holy Campe. <hi>Waſh thy heart, Ier.</hi> 4, 14. everie one his heart. <hi>Purge your hands yee ſinners, and purifie your hearts ye double minded. Iam. 4. Everie one that hath this hope purgeth himſelf, euen as Chriſt is pure. 1 Iohn 3.5.</hi> And for example to the reſt, let the <hi>Leaders</hi> and <hi>Chiefteins, Heads</hi> and <hi>Commanders</hi> firſt be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>If the eye be ſingle, the whole bodie is full of light:</hi> if they who are chief in place be holy: ſo will the reſt be alſo. It was admirablie ſpoken of Ioſhuah, chap. 24. that <hi>he and his houſe would ſerue the Lord:</hi> Firſt he, and then his houſe, never would his houſe be, if he would not goe before in reformation. So ſhould everie <hi>Worthie</hi> in the <hi>Lords</hi> Camp ſay: I and my Souldiers will be holy, and firſt be a <hi>patterne</hi> himſelfe of holynes to them, and be a living and walking image of <hi>Gods</hi> holines among them. Againe <hi>Iudg. 7.17. Looke on me and do likewiſe,</hi> ſaid <hi>Gideon</hi> to his men. So they would, no queſtion, behold him, and doe as he ſhould doe. Nothing poyſons a Campe more, then when the infection begins at the head. If the fountaine be bitter,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2, 21.</note> the ſtreames can be no better. When <hi>Officers,</hi> and ſuch as ſhould be <hi>preſidents</hi> and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of holynes to the reſt, when I ſay, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, prophane, no marvell though the private <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier</hi> be no better. When they will drinke drunke, when they will ſweare, and ſwagger, when they will take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious libertie to themſelues, it is no wonder, though their followers doe ſo toe. Secondly; <hi>Gods</hi> holy <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> muſt be in the Campe. The <hi>word</hi> eſpecially, or trueth of God. and <hi>Diſcipline, divine</hi> and <hi>militarie.</hi> The Diſcipline of <hi>Gods</hi> word, to ſuſpend from the <hi>Sacrament</hi> indifferently, all obſtinate unholy perſons, to ſever the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15213:23"/>cleane from the uncleane, <hi>the precious from the vile. Ier.</hi> 15, 19. And <hi>diſcipline militarie,</hi> muſt not lye dead, but muſt be exerciſed impartially, upon one and other offending, and ſo, ſecond the former: Els your preachers may teach holynes, till their braines fall out at their browes, and to none end. This then muſt be exerciſed in purging your Camps of open and notorious ſinners and ſinnes, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes of <hi>ſtewes,</hi> drunckennes. And none muſt be borne with, nor ſuffred, that will not be reformed. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. <hi>I will early deſtroy all the wicked of the land, and cutte off all wicked doers from the cittie of my God. Prov.</hi> 20.26. <hi>A wiſe king ſcattereth the wicked, and bringeth the wheele over them.</hi> that is, incorrigible wicked ones, whom no other meanes will do good unto. See, for the exerciſe of <hi>Martiall diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> in the Lords Campe <hi>Exod.</hi> 32, 27. <hi>Put everie man his ſword by his ſide, and goe in and out thoroughout the Campe, and ſlaye, &amp;c. Levit.</hi> 24.16. <hi>He that blaſpheameth the name of the Lord ſhall ſurely be put to death. Numb.</hi> 25. The juſt puniſhment of <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi</hi> for their wicked preſumption. But as once the Prophet, ſo may we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, <hi>Habac.</hi> 1, 4. <hi>The law is ſlacked, &amp;c.</hi> an elegant me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor from the <hi>pulſe,</hi> which in a dying man beates faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and retires: ſo when the law of juſt diſcipline beginns to ſlacken, it argues a dying <hi>reipublique,</hi> and is verie omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous. As they had their paddle readie to rid the Campe of their excrements: ſo muſt Diſcipline be uſed to ridde the tents of all the wicked excrements of ſinne. And as <hi>Christ</hi> whipt the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple: ſo be couragious, you whom it concerneth, to reforme all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities. And looke eſpecially to thoſe tippling-places in your Camps, the verie ſincks, and nurſeries of all impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. It followeth in the 17 <hi>verſe. There ſhall be no whore of the Daughters of Iſraell, nor a Sodomite of the ſonnes of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15213:24"/>Iſrael,</hi> meaning none permitted. <hi>Num.</hi> 5, 2, 3. <hi>Command the Children of Iſrael, that they put out of the Campe, everie Leaper, everie one that hath an iſsue, whoſoever is defiled by the dead, both male and female ſhall ye put out, without the Campe ſhall ye put them, that they defile not their Camps, in the mids of whom I dwell.</hi> Muſt <hi>Leapers</hi> be put out, and ſhall they be ſuffred in the Camp, who haue a worſe <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie,</hi> of all wickednes, cleaving unto them, to infect all they come neare? So then, the word of <hi>God</hi> which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his holy and bleſſed trueth, muſt be diligently taught, by holy men, whoſe liues may caſt forth holynes to others. And the ordinances of Diſcipline <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticall, ſubordinate to the word.</hi> The one is to plant, the other to preſerue holynes in us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly; <hi>to make choiſe,</hi> as neare as we can, <hi>of the best men.</hi> What hopes of a holy Camp, when the ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not pickt, whereof the <hi>Romans</hi> were not a little care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as may be ſeene in their wars. By <hi>making choyce of the beſt men,</hi> I meane not, the beſt <hi>timbred men,</hi> but the beſt conditioned: not onely he that hath not a tattred out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, but whoſe minde is not ragged. Make option of the moſt ſtayed, civill, and beſt diſpoſed, and not ſuch as <hi>Iepthah</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam</hi> entertained, <hi>vaine men Iudg.</hi> 11.3. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.7. The ſkumme of men, fitter to fill <hi>priſons</hi> and <hi>Iayles,</hi> then places of better note; &amp; to become <hi>dennes of theeues,</hi> then an <hi>armie of Saints.</hi> Such (as one ſayth) who if the Diuell ſhould offer a ſtipend unto, would not refuſe him ſervice, and be more faythfull to him, though it were to beare armes againſt <hi>God</hi> himſelf. How happie were it, if our Camps were rid of ſuch. And I haue often thought, that if, as we find <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7. they that had built houſes, and had not dedicated them; planted vineyards, and had not eaten of the fruite of them, betrothed wiues,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15213:24"/>and had not taken them, I ſay, if they muſt be caſheired and be gone from <hi>Iſraels</hi> Campe, what ſhould a world of our debauched men, profeſſed <hi>drunkards, robbers, ſwearers, fornicators</hi> and ſuch like cattell, I wonder what they ſhould haue done there? I know, we haue not all ſuch (God forbid!) but ſome not more noble in blood then in vertue, ſtayed, ſober, religious men, fearing <hi>God,</hi> and eſchewing evill, in great meaſure: but the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſuch is rare, and of the other multiplying. What is the reaſon we haue ſo many of the one ſort, and ſo few of the other? Is it becauſe the good are fewer, and we cannot get them? which alſo is true; but is it not rather, becauſe we ſtand not (a great number of us) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the grace, and goodnes of the men we take on, whether there be any bluſh, or appearance of any in them, chuſing our men, as <hi>Samuel</hi> and the reſt would haue choſen a <hi>King, 1 Sam. 16, 6, 7.
<note place="margin">Sed quotuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt (non iniqua cuiuſda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaerela) qui non malit stre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> milite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pium: imo ne locus quident amplius in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitu (horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum fane!) piis relinquitur</note> looking on his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, or the height of his ſtature,</hi> things I confeſſe to be regarded, but that is not all: there is ſomewhat els to be looked after, that we may poſſibly make an holy camp. But, if we cannot doe withall, but we muſt take ſuch as we can (a miſerable neceſſitie) as the <hi>Romans</hi> ſometime were conſtreyned, to uſe ſclaues for the defenſe of their common weale, yet when they are under us, let us cauſe them to be outwardly at leaſt conformable to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, and labour, that they may be inſtructed, to the end, that holynes which grew not in them before, may now come up. Plant amongſt you a <hi>godly</hi> and painfull miniſtrie, and ſubject your ſelues, and your men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
            <p>And theſe be the principall meanes to make a holy Campe, we can doe no more then propound them, and pray the Lord to giue you hearts to improue them.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15213:25"/>And the rather to ſtirre you up, hearken to a motiue, two or three, for the concluſion of this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motiues toward a holy Campe, and holynes in our perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is; <hi>Holynes</hi> will call more unto us, and make men more in loue with our profeſſion, from which many are, and may be juſtly daunted, becauſe, holynes is ſo great a ſtranger to us. The Complaint hath been old, but as true as ancient:
<q>Rara fides, pietaſque viris, qui caſtra ſequuntur.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, manie are out of loue with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and forſweare the Campe, which with unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourie ſinne of all ſortes, doeth ſtinke in the noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrils of the world, or the civiller ſort of it. Oh how many would <hi>Sanctitie</hi> and true <hi>reformation</hi> in our Camps invite unto us, and what a glorie holynes would adde to our profeſſion, honourable in it ſelfe, but would be double honourable, by the acquiſition of this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly; The continuall dangers we are in, and ſubject unto, calleth upon us to labour to be holy. For then, let what come can come, we are ready for death, if that be readie for us. Then mayeſt thou ſay with <hi>Conrades</hi> in the <hi>hyſtorie:
<note place="margin">Generall hyſt. of the Turks pag 33.</note> Let the Perſian Archer ſtrike me, I will dye in an aſſured hope, and with that arrow, as with a Chariot, come unto that rest, which ſhall be dearer to me, then if I ſhould with a baſe ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie kinde of death, in my ſinnes, ende my dayes in my bedde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; then ſhall you be ſure of Gods gracious preſence among you for good, and againſt all evil; plainly intimated here. If they would labour for a holy Camp, they ſhould haue the holy <hi>Lord</hi> among them, whoſe preſence ſhould be all in all to them,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15213:25"/>but if otherwiſe, let us not expect <hi>God</hi> among us, unleſſe it be to confound our armies. It ſuites not with a <hi>King,</hi> to walke in dung-hills, or to be ſeene in noyſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and will God walke among our Camps, if we haue no care to ſweepe his paths?</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond branch</hi> of this <hi>Concluſion</hi> followeth: <hi>That he ſee no uncleannes in thee.</hi> Which is the <hi>negatiue</hi> part of the <hi>order</hi> touching their Camp. <hi>Holynes</hi> there muſt be, <hi>uncleannes</hi> there ſhould not be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>uncleannes] Ervah</hi> ſignifieth nakednes, and denoteth that uncomely part, whereon man beſtoweth more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant honour. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 9. <hi>Cham</hi> diſcovered the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his Father. So called in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> becauſe it ſhould alwaies be covered. Sinne being denominated nakednes in the <hi>ſacred</hi> tongue, argues the manner of ſinns attaching us by propagation: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>In ſinne did my Mother warme me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation</hi> 4. <hi>Sinne is a nakednes:</hi> the Greeke ſaith,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervat. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>a ſhame. Geneſ.</hi> 3. Our firſt parents were naked; ſinne had made them ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſect.</hi> 1. Oh then labour to be aſhamed of it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>What fruit had ye in thoſe things, whereof you are now aſhamed?</hi> Bluſh for ſhame, and be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in thy ſelfe, O Sinner. We can be aſhamed of bodily nakednes, of ſpirituall nakednes we are not. A worſe nakednes is this then any other, for it is a naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes joyned with filthie deformitie, and miſſhapenes: men are not aſhamed alwaies to be ſeene naked, but when they are deformed, miſmade, and ugly: this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of ſinne, is the greateſt deformitie, that can be imagined: The ugly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> monſtrous <hi>Old man</hi> is without al forme or beautie. But, as with ſome people the pureſt black is the pureſt bewtie: ſo is it with ſome men, the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15213:26"/>fowleſt black and ſoote of ſinne, is bewtie in their eyes.</p>
            <p>Secondly; labour, oh labour to haue ſinne, which is thy nakednes covered, not by excuſing and hiding it, but rather by uncovering it to God. <hi>Bleſsed is the man whoſe iniquitie is forgiuen, and whoſe ſinne is covered.</hi> Men will not ſuffer their filthie nakednes to be ſeene, and therefore, they will clap, and keepe their garments about them, and rather weare ragged, then none at all. Yet all covering externall will never hide this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall nakednes. Bodily nakednes requires bodily co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, and that is enough: Spirituall nakednes requires ſpirituall covering: <hi>Put ye on therefore the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he ſee no uncleannes in thee.]</hi> The Hebrew phraſe may be read two wayes, firſt, <hi>the nakednes of a thing,</hi> an <hi>uncleane buſines,</hi> or <hi>matter;</hi> that <hi>he ſee not an unſeemely thing in thee.</hi> Or ſecondly, any <hi>nakednes,</hi> or <hi>unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> any at all, ſo <hi>dhabhar</hi> is taken, to ſignifie <hi>any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation</hi> 5.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>God muſt ſee no uncleannes, or impuritie of ſinne among us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is, becauſe he cannot abide it. <hi>Ieſ.</hi> 1, 13. his rejecting their oblations, and hating their ſacrifices, was the rejecting and hating their ſinns. <hi>Bring no more vaine oblations, incenſe is abhomination, the new Moones and Sabaoths, and calling of aſſemblies I cannot away with.</hi> (a ſpeech of extream indignation) and what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, what cannot he away with his owne ordinances? <hi>it is iniquitie,</hi> ſayth he. Iniquitie <hi>God</hi> cannot endure: <hi>verſe</hi> 14. <hi>Your new Moones and your appointed feaſts my ſoule hateth, they are a trouble to me. I am wearie.</hi> Sinne is a trouble to the <hi>Lord. Waſh you, waſh you,</hi> ſayth he, what doe you with this uncleannes upon you, which I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15213:26"/>cannot away with. <hi>Conſect.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Why then, happie are <hi>Gods</hi> Children; for he, <hi>ſeeth no iniquitie in Iacob, nor tranſgreſsion in Iſraell. Num.</hi> 23. Not becauſe he cannot, but becauſe he will not, and he caſts a covering of his ſonne upon them. Should <hi>God</hi> ſee uncleannes in us, he ſhould breake out upon us. <hi>Lord</hi> if thou beholdeſt iniquitie, who can ſtand. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130, 3.</p>
            <p>Secondly; we muſt therefore, beware of defiling our ſelues with ſinne, the rather. When <hi>Children</hi> are uncleane by rude behaviour, all bemired and dirtie, they are afraid of their Fathers ſight: ſo ſhould we be afraid, that <hi>God</hi> ſhould ſee the uncleannes of any ſinne in us, from whom we cannot hide it. In the 24 chapt. of <hi>Deut. verſe</hi> 1. it was permitted, that if a man had perceived <hi>Ervath dabhar, anie uncleannes</hi> in her whom he had taken to wife unto him, he might put her away: and will <hi>God</hi> joyne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to us, if we cheriſh the uncleannes of ſinne in us?</p>
            <p>The ſecond generall thing is, the <hi>reaſon</hi> of the <hi>order for</hi> holynes, and <hi>against</hi> uncleannes in them; follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in theſe laſt words ſaying; <hi>And turne away from thee,</hi> or, from after thee. Hebr. The <hi>Chalde</hi> ſayth here, <hi>leaſt his WORD turne away from doing good unto thee.</hi> See this of turning away from them, to doe them good. <hi>Ier.</hi> 32, 40.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation</hi> 6. <hi>Sinne forceth God to leaue,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>6</label> and turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from a people,</hi> and that <hi>in great diſpleaſure. Iſ.</hi> 59.2. <hi>Your iniquities haue ſeparated betweene you and your God.</hi> Sinne, (ſayth one) is a <hi>Schiſmatique.</hi> And this is the <hi>Schiſme</hi> and rent which it makes betweene <hi>God</hi> and us. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5, 15. <hi>I will goe and returne unto my place, till they acknowledge their offence.</hi> Meaning (as here he ſpeakes) he would turne away from them. So the <hi>Lord</hi> turned
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15213:27"/>away from <hi>Sampſon. Iudg.</hi> the 16. and 20 verſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>reaſon</hi> is firſt; that which was partly giuen in the former point, he cannot endure ſinne, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. <hi>He is a God of pure eyes, and cannot looke upon ſinn,</hi> a moſt impure object.</p>
            <p>Secondly; Sinne is that which turnes away from his law [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] and the righteouſnes of his nature, and is moſt contrarie to him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly; Sinne turnes us away from <hi>God,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Lord</hi> turnes away from ſinne, and us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſect.</hi> 1. Why then, it is no ſmall matter for <hi>God</hi> to turne away from his people. And this appears al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the bitter complaint hereof, in the church of <hi>God,</hi> among his people, when <hi>God</hi> had turned from them, and the woefull effects thereof, threatned <hi>Deutr.</hi> 31, 17. <hi>I will forſake them, and hide my face from them, and many evils and troubles ſhall befall them. Lord</hi> it is no marvell, though many evils doe befall us, when thou the fountaine of all good doeſt leaue us! <hi>Hoſea 9, 12. Yea, woe unto them, when I departe from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As when the Sunne goeth away from our Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, he turnes away all his light and comfort from us, and leaues us to grope in darkenes: ſo when God turnes away from us, we are bereaved of all good. He turnes not away alone; The <hi>Sunne</hi> when he comes to us, comes with a great deale of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, with much refreſhing through his bright ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rayes, and ſweete influence of his beames. (And <hi>truly the light is ſweete, and a pleaſant thing is it to behould the Sunne, Eccleſ. 11.7.) God</hi> is a <hi>Sunne</hi> of bleſſed influence where he commeth, <hi>(I will be a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15213:27"/>Sunne, and a ſhielde Pſalm.</hi> 84.) and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſayd to ariſe like the Sunne, <hi>The Sunne of righteouſnes ſhall ariſe with healing in his wings, and ye ſhall grow up as Calues, and goe forth. Mal. 4.2.</hi> So, when <hi>God</hi> comes to a people, he comes with a great deale of peace, and happines; and when he leaues any, and turnes himſelfe away, he turnes and takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all his mercies. <hi>Your iniquities haue turned away theſe things,</hi> that is, all thoſe good things before ſpoken of) and <hi>your ſinnes haue withholden good things from you. Ierem. 5.25. I haue taken away my peace from this people, euen loving kindnes and mercies. Ier. 16, 5.</hi> Firſt, <hi>God</hi> takes himſelfe away, or we by our ſinnes and foule tranſgreſſions turne <hi>God</hi> away, and looſe all bleſſing with him. As when the <hi>King</hi> goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, his <hi>court</hi> followes him, his attendants, and all goe away with him, and nothing remaines but a naked place: ſo when God turneth away, his Court of attendance, and all thoſe good things, as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitants, doe wheele about with him. Which, aboue all things in the world, ſhould make us care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as we tender the reſidence of God among us, yea as we tender our liues, the life of our liues, that by Sinne, we turne not God away from us. <hi>For the Ioye of the Lord is our ſtrength. Nehem. 8, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly; this ſhould teach us, that we ſhould no ſooner ſee uncleannes and ſinne, but like God, away we ſhould turne our ſelues from it, with loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing indignation. As when we behould an object leſſe ſavorie, and pleaſing to our ſent and ſight, we turne away and goe aſide, hide our eyes, and ſtop our noſes: ſo there ſhould no evill boldly preſent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15213:28"/>it ſelfe to us, but we ſhould divert our ſelues. And ſo it ſhould appeare, that there is ſomewhat of that true hatred of ſinne in us, which is moſt infinitely in <hi>God,</hi> which if we did, <hi>God</hi> would the leſſe, nay not at all turne away from us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and laſtly; Behold here, the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomenes of ſinne, the vileneſſe and the filthineſſe thereof, moſt intollerable, in that it makes the Lord turne away from us, yea from his beloved people.</p>
            <p>Nothing (my Brethren,) can be ſo odious to us, to make us turne away in diſdaine, to make us forſake and withdraw our ſelues from it, as ſinne and uncleanneſſe is to GOD. It is that which forceth him to abandon his people with a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie <hi>dereliction,</hi> untill they returne: and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with an eternall deſertion.</p>
            <p>It muſt be a great matter muſt make us turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from thoſe who are deare unto us. Gods people are his children, it muſt be a ſtrange thing muſt make a Father turne away from his children. They are his Spowſe, and therefore Sinne is ſome greate abhomination, that conſtreineth the Lord to leaue them.</p>
            <p>When we turne away from any thing, we turne away from a Serpent, from a Baſiliske, from a Toade, from a ſtincking Carkaſſe, which is moſt noyſome, or, wee turne away from our enimies, whom we hate, and of whom we are hated. Some diſpleaſing <hi>obiect</hi> or other it alwaies is, which we turne away from. We never turne away from that which is amiable, louely and faire: but what
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15213:28"/>is accurſed, and miſerable, and worthilie of it ſelfe to be deteſted, oh what an abhominable and beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing is ſinne, a moſt uncleane uncleanneſſe, and impure impuritie, which makes <hi>God</hi> to turne away from us, becauſe of that?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
